<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spirit of the church-faction detected, in its nature and operations more particularly in the mystery of the convocation-book lately published and exposed to the view and censure of the world by the late Arch-Bishop of Canterbury, and the progress of the faction, and the mischiefs thereof, the late civil war, and our present disappointments.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61448</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24618</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08255735</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08255735</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41226</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61448)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41226)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1241:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spirit of the church-faction detected, in its nature and operations more particularly in the mystery of the convocation-book lately published and exposed to the view and censure of the world by the late Arch-Bishop of Canterbury, and the progress of the faction, and the mischiefs thereof, the late civil war, and our present disappointments.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41226:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41226:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SPIRIT OF The Church-Faction DETECTED, In its Nature and Operations, More Particularly in The <hi>Myſtery</hi> of the <hi>Convocation-Book,</hi> Lately Publiſhed and Expoſed To the <hi>View</hi> and <hi>Cenſure</hi> of the World, by the late Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury:</hi> And in The <hi>Progreſs</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> And the <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> thereof, The late <hi>Civil War,</hi> and our preſent <hi>Diſappointments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, MDCXCI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:41226:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Lately publiſh'd by the ſame Author.</head>
            <p>AN <hi>Admonition</hi> concerning <hi>a Publick FAST;</hi> The Juſt <hi>Cauſes</hi> we have for it, from the full <hi>Growth</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> and the near <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches</hi> of God's <hi>Judgments;</hi> And the <hi>Manner</hi> of Performance, to obtain the deſired Effects thereof; Which ought to be other than our Common Forms; and with ſtricter Acts of Mortification than is uſual amongſt us.</p>
            <p>An APPEAL to <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> againſt the <hi>Chriſtian Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureans,</hi> who have betrayed their KING and <hi>Countrey,</hi> and Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to the <hi>Judgments</hi> of <hi>GOD;</hi> Drawn up in Queſtions <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical,</hi> and <hi>Theologico-Political.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:41226:2"/>
            <head>A CAVEAT to the READER.</head>
            <p>IT is certain that <hi>Mankind</hi> is commonly very prone to that Folly of <hi>running out of one Extream into another:</hi> And it is as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and apparent that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> all over the World being <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided</hi> into ſeveral different Parties, are generally (where they have any Zeal at all) <hi>more zealous for their own particular Parties,</hi> and for thoſe things which are peculiar to them, <hi>than for Chriſtianity it ſelf,</hi> or the Great matters of it, in which all agree: and that accordingly they are generally <hi>more led and ſwayed by the Comments</hi> and Doctrines of their Teachers and leading men of their reſpective Parties, and the Opinion they have of them, <hi>than by the plain Text</hi> of the S. Scripture, and the Authority thereof, though they do not apprehend ſo much themſelves. All this might be <hi>proved</hi> by many Evidences of Fact: but that would be too long for this place; and beſides it is needleſs: For all acknowledge it to be ſo in all parties but their own; which is ſufficient Evidence, as good as need be, againſt all; for their own Confeſſion againſt themſelves is not to be expected. And all acknowledge it to be a Fault, wherever it is.</p>
            <p>This I note for Caution, and to prevent that ill <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe which might be made of what I have here written for a good End; (<hi>viz.</hi> that the Church of <hi>England</hi> might be moved to Reform of her ſelf what is amiſs, to caſt out all Abuſes, and extirpate all thoſe peſtiferous Weeds and Roots of Faction,) and in caſe that God for her Negligence ſhould a ſecond time leave her to the Correction of any other Party, that they may not again overſhoot themſelves, and by inconſiderate heat, inſtead of Reformation put all into Confuſion; or by Severity againſt their fellow Servants, provoke the Judgments of their common Lord againſt themſelves. For all have their Faults, and very conſiderable ones too: and moſt have ſome Good almoſt peculiar to themſelves, which the reſt either overlook or neglect, if not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or obſtinately refuſe. Even that very party which hath moſt Weeds of all, may, and if I be not deceived, often doth produce ſuch Fruit amongſt thoſe Weeds, as can hardly be matcht by any of the other; which muſt therefore have the more to anſwer for, that under a better Culture they do not bring forth better, and more mature and excellent Fruit. Had we been as carefull to retain and improve what was good, and to reſtore and repair what was loſt or decayed, as we were to caſt out all that was bad,
<pb facs="tcp:41226:3"/>our Work had been more compleat, and ſucceſsfull. But while Heat of Contention makes all Parties apt to take the matters in Controverſie for the great Matters of Religion, what are really the Great Matters of Religion, are the leſs regarded by any, and what are taken to be ſo, but are not, are proſecuted and preſſed further than they ought to be, by each reſpectively when they get the Advantage for it.</p>
            <p>Such were the Superſtitions and ſuperfluous Rites, whereby the genuine Simple and moſt Proper and Decent <hi>Chriſtian Worſhip of God,</hi> was in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> corrupted and obſcured, like good Wheat in a Great heap of Tares and Chaff, that many to avoid them have run into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Superſtition, avoiding and neglecting even natural expreſſions of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Decency in it, and little leſs than Prophaneneſs. This juſtly moved ſome of our Biſhops, and Dr. <hi>Laud</hi> eſpecially, when he came into favour, to labour, as he ſaith, <hi>That the External Worſhip of God (ſo much ſlighted in many parts) might be preſerved, and that with as much Decency and Uniformity as might be.</hi> But it was preſſed too far, in unneceſſary matters, in a kind of arbitrary manner, without an equal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for the promotion of real and internal Piety; nay, with obſtinate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal and oppoſition of Reformation of other great Abuſes, in Diſcipline, Non-Reſidence, Pluralities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and with Oppoſition even of ſome Means of the promotion of Religion, the Obſervation of the Lords Day, Lectures, And the purchaſe of Impropriations, as if it was the only thing neceſſary, or it and abſolute Subjection to the Will of the Prince under the Notion of Loyalty, was the ſumme of all Religion. And this again on the other ſide, made it be looked upon as meer Formality, and a Project to prepare us for the readmiſſion of Popery, and ſo raiſed a greater Antipathy againſt it; which at laſt caſt all out, but in its place brought in Indecency, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs and Confuſion. But we have now a Choice of ſuch Biſhops, as I hope will make a better uſe of what I have written, and do their parts to make this Caution needleſs.</p>
            <p>For the Readers better ſatisfaction concerning the near agreement of the Nature and Genius of our <hi>Church-Faction</hi> with that of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I recommend to his peruſal and Conſideration Dr. <hi>Barrow</hi>'s Account of the Inconveniences of the Papal Pretences, <hi>pag. 201.</hi> to <hi>pag. 214. Of the Popes Supremacy.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41226:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE SPIRIT OF THE Church-Faction DETECTED, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Have formerly taken notice of a certain Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Church-Faction,</hi> and the True <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> and the ingenious Dr. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible: scratched out" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hath larely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the Honourable <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> and the World ſince in a Sermon now in Print, with a notable and very true diſtinction between <hi>the Spirit of God,</hi> and <hi>the Spirit of the Church of England;</hi> which muſt be underſtood of <hi>the Church-Faction,</hi> which arrogates to it ſelf the Name of <hi>the Church of England,</hi> as its Mother the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth the Name of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> and with as good Right and Reaſon every whit. Of <hi>this Faction</hi> I ſay it muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; for the True <hi>Church of England</hi> owns no Spirit for its Guide but <hi>that of God.</hi> And ſince he hath furniſhed us with ſo uſefull and remarkable a Diſtinction, to whom can we more properly have recourſe to underſtand the Nature of this Spirit, than to him who profeſſeth himſelf poſſeſſed of it? and beſides, is very free and apt upon all occaſions to afford Experiments and plain Demonſtrations of its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Vertues and Faculties? And one he hath lately given
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41226:4"/>in the Caſe of Mr. <hi>David Jones,</hi> and that ſo notable an one, as may fully ſatisfie all men who conſider it well, which I will therefore briefly relate.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> had twice preached here in <hi>London,</hi> for a Miniſter who was abſent; and at the ſecond time, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make ſome ſtay in Town,) he was deſired by ſome perſons of other Pariſhes, who had either heard him or heard of him, to preach at their Churches, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly at St. <hi>Andrews</hi> and <hi>Chriſt-church,</hi> both the ſame day, 2 <hi>Nov.</hi> Thereupon, conſidering the quality of thoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditories, he made choice of a Sermon which he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly made at <hi>Oxford,</hi> upon 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Charge them that are rich in this world, that they be not high-minded:</hi> And diſcourſing upon the parts of his Text in order, as is uſual, before he came to diſcourſe of the Rich, which he principally intended, from the firſt word he touched upon the <hi>Miniſterial Charge,</hi> and the Neglect thereof by many <hi>Pluraliſts, Chaplains</hi> and other <hi>Non-Reſidents,</hi> and others deſerting then former Charges for temporal Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. And this paſſed well enough in the Morning at S. <hi>Andrewes,</hi> where there were none preſent who were much concerned in it: But in the Afternoon at <hi>Chriſt-Church,</hi> Dr. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible: scratched out" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> being there, who hath a Cure in the Countrey, two Lectures in the City, is the Kings Chaplain, and a Noble-mans Chaplain beſides; all this ſeem'd deſigned di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt him, eſpecially being preached by one of his own Colledge. And thereupon, as Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> was going from the Pulpit to the Veſtry, the Dr. came to him, and after ſome hard words took him by the ſhoulder, and bid him be gone out of the Church; adding, That he would take care he ſhould come no more there to tell them of their Faults.</p>
            <p>This ſtrange carriage of the Dr. occaſioned much Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; and that, and the Efferveſcence of his own Paſſion, made him not only break out into foul and falſe Aſperſions
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41226:4"/>of Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> in all Companies the Week following, but into indecent Reflections upon him even from the Pulpit, the next Lords day. This moved a Friend of Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> who was then at Church, to go to the Dr. afteward into the Veſtry, to expoſtulate the matter calmly with him. But the Dr. could not contain himſelf, but preſently fell into paſſion; and threatned, he would deſire thoſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (who ſtood there by) to ſerve him, as he had ſerved Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> the Sunday before: To which the other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, If he were of that temper, he ſhould not need to trouble himſelf, for he had no more to ſay to him; and ſo left him; but the next day wrote him the following Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Reverend Dr.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am very ſorry that ſuch a Difference ſhould fall out, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two Perſons ſo qualified to do good ſervice in the Church, as may prove ſome Impediment to both: It becomes men of your Profeſſion to be mutual Aſſiſtants to one another in the promotion of the Work and Service of your common Maſter. And therefore that the Evil of the Difference may be prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſtopped, and if poſſible turned to good, I beg your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to peruſe and ſeriouſly conſider theſe few things, which I ſhall as briefly as I can, and with all candor and impartiality offer to your conſideration. I am of opinion that (as it uſually falls out in moſt differences, ſo in this,) there may be ſome fault on both ſides.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> I take to be in the right in the Subſtance of what he delivered, but may have erred a little in Circumſtance, in the Seaſon of his delivering it. But yet in Charity that ought to be imputed to the height of his Zeal for the Reformation of things <hi>notoriouſly</hi> amiſs, and of great Importance to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. And as his unblamable and ſtrict Life obligeth us to make this conſtruction of it; ſo the great and notorious Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Governours of our Church, makes his Reproof, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41226:5"/>in ſeaſon or out of ſeaſon, excuſable at leaſt, if not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable: And if you or any other of the Clergy offer to give him any Diſturbance for it, I dare aſſure you, you will but ſo much the more expoſe your ſelves and a foul Cauſe. It will be more agreeable to Chriſtianity, and the places you hold in the Church, to humble your ſelves before God, and ſet ſpeedily about ſuch a Reformation as may make ſuch Preaching needleſs. And for Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> I hope I ſhall be able to prevail with him to conſider better of the Seaſon for thoſe things, but not to remit any thing of his warmth againſt them in due ſeaſon, untill I ſee more Zeal for the Reformation of them in others.</p>
                  <p>But your Fault (pardon my plain dealing, which proceeds not from ill will, but to do you good,) is in the Subſtance of what is amiſs. You have undertaken (as I am informed) the greateſt Charge in the World, the Cure of Souls, and neglect it; leave it to a Hireling, who if he be as good a man as your ſelf, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves as much, that is all the Profits; if he be not, you do not diſcharge your Duty there. And you not only neglect ſo great a Charge, but neglect it for the World, for the Profit of a Lecture, nay two Lectures; and in a place where there is no need of your Help, where there are Labourers who want Work, and ſome who want Subſiſtence beſides: So that the ſin of your Neglect is aggravated with great Scandal, tempting People both to Worldly-mindedneſs, and to ſuſpect that you, an eminent Dr. either believe not the Doctrine you profeſs, and ſo alſo to Atheiſm; or that you believe not the ſtrict Obſervation thereof to be neceſſary, and ſo at leaſt to Licentiouſneſs: and aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not only with Scandal, but with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs too, and that even to men of your own Kind, through ſuch <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſatiable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>V.</hi> Iſa. 6.11.</note> Canine Appetite, which not only preys upon the Flock, but devours the very Shepherds. Nor is this all yet; for you plainly encourage and lead into ſin the People you preach to. If to covet another mans Servant be a Sin, contrary to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Command of God, then certainly to inveigle another mans Servant from him is a greater Sin: And if this be ſo, what is it then to inveigle the Miniſter of a whole Pariſh from the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41226:5"/>ſervice of their Souls? And no leſs a ſin than this are all they guilty of who contribute to either of your Lectures. The due conſideration of this, and what it is to be partakers in other mens ſins, as they are in all yours before mentioned, is fit to be recommended to your Auditors. And a due ſenſe of theſe things, (had you bin in nothing elſe concerned in that diſcourſe) would have allayed and checked the intemperance of your Paſſion againſt a juſt Reproof, which I am certain was not deſigned by any man for your perſon more than for any other, but ordered it ſeems by the Providence of God to fall upon you, for your Correction, and your Good, if it be not your own fault</p>
                  <p>But to all this, inſtead of that Chriſtian uſe you ought to have made of it, you added another fault, by your paſſionate and indecent <hi>Treatment</hi> of him for it, in ſuch a manner as had not bin excuſable had you bin Rector, but was much leſs ſo in you, who have only ſo precarious an Intereſt in that Church, as only Lecturer, and ſuch as you cannot retain without ſin both in your ſelf, and in thoſe who contribute to it.</p>
                  <p>And yet to this you have ſince added a third in your Sermon yeſterday, [on <hi>Act. 26.29.</hi> concerning <hi>Reproof, that it ought to be mild and gentle.</hi>] For, <hi>1.</hi> It was an Abuſe of Religion and of the Doctrine of the Goſpel, to make uſe of it to gratifie your Paſſion in Indecent Reflections. <hi>2.</hi> It was imprudently done in your Caſe, in as much as thoſe Reflections do all rebound and more notoriouſly fall upon pour ſelf, who had juſtly and inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſably deſerved the worſt you could ſay to that purpoſe. <hi>3.</hi> You did not handle that Doctrine faithfully: for tho ſuch as are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in a fault are to be reſtored in a ſpirit of meekneſs, yet ſuch as ſin deliberately are to be ſharply reproved: And this being your own caſe, and whereof you were admoniſhed, you did not at all touch upon it; but handled the Word of God deceitfully, like thoſe falſe Prophets who propheſied ſmooth things. <hi>(Iſa. 30.10.)</hi> Your paſſionate Carriage afterward in the Veſtry, to my ſelf, who was willing to have diſcourſed theſe things calmly with you, I paſs by: but expect your Anſwer to this, and ſhall be ready, without any further regard to what is paſt, to treat with you as your
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41226:6"/>future and better Carriage ſhall deſerve, and hoping the beſt ſhall remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Humble Servant. <hi>E. S.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <date>
                        <hi>10 Nov. 1690.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Had the Dr. upon peruſal of this Letter well conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed how unhappily he had fallen into a Quarrel, which in Prudence he ought to have avoided at firſt, and however to let fall as ſoon and as ſilently as might be, 'tis likely it might have paſſed over with a little talk only for a few dayes. But as for the Letter, he told the Meſſenger who carried it, and deſired his Anſwer, that he had nothing to do with Mr. <hi>S.</hi> (who wrote it) and he would ſend him no Anſwer: And for Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> nothing leſs than to have him Suſpended or Silenced could ſatisfie that Spirit he is of, whatſoever it is. And it was not long before ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Occaſion raiſed him up ſome Companions in the ſame Cauſe againſt Mr. <hi>Jones.</hi> For notwithſtanding this Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by that Doctor, he made bold in another Sermon the next Lords Day, or the next but one, to touch two other Faults of many of our Clergy, <hi>viz. Neglect of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing,</hi> and <hi>Admiſſion of ſcandalous Perſons to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament:</hi> And theſe two Sermons (though it was unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable Truth in them, at which they took ſuch Offence) preſently raiſed ſuch a Spirit in many of the Clergy about the City, that no leſs than forty or fifty, as is reported, at one Meeting, agreed together that none of them ſhould permit <hi>David Jones</hi> to Preach in his Pulpit; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly a Pulpit which was Promiſed by one of them for a Stranger the next Lords day was denyed as ſoon as it was known that <hi>David Jones</hi> was the Man. And afterwards at another Meeting, or ſome way or other amongſt them, they ſo prevailed with the Biſhop, that he would neither permit him to Preach without a Licenſe, though that is ſeldom or never required of Strangers in <hi>London;</hi> nor let
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41226:6"/>him have a Licenſe, though he was willing to take one, and pay the Fees, having an abſolute Promiſe to be Choſen to a Place in <hi>London</hi> if he might have a Licenſe. So that after ten Years hard Study in the Univerſity, and a ſober and ſtrict Life, he is by the Spirit of this Party kept from the Service of God in the Exerciſe of his Miniſtry, to which he is Ordained according to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and from a Livelihood in his Calling, for no other Fault but Preaching againſt the Faults of others, whilſt thoſe who are guilty thereof are not only connived at, but favoured even in their unreaſonable, and not more imprudent than im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent Proſecution of one, who did but reprove them. And this Dr. being not only guilty of thoſe Faults, but more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over a principal Agent in this Proſecution, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the private Admonition of that Letter, ſince that had no better effect upon him, it was thought fit to make it publick; and the rather becauſe by ſome Expreſſions of the Biſhops, the Letter ſeems to have been either miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to him, or miſtaken by him.</p>
            <p>And thus much for <hi>David Jones</hi> his Caſe, which, though very hard, yet being only a private Caſe, I ſhould not have thought ſit to have made thus publick, did it not preſent us with a conſiderable Inſtance of the Nature of that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Spirit, which hath brought both the Church and the State of this Nation into a moſt dangerous Condition, and very near to a moſt diſmal Cataſtrophe; and with a fair Occaſion to detect its Nature and Operations before it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the ſame in the Confuſion and final Deſtruction of both.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt</hi> it is very plain that this is none of the Spirit of God or of Chriſt, for that is pure, peaceable, gentle,<note place="margin">Jam. 3.</note> and eaſie to be entreated, full of Mercy and good Fruits; and theſe Fruits (to judge according to our Saviour's Rule) are Love, Joy, Peace, Long ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> Faith, Meekneſs, Temperance, and the like;<note place="margin">Gal. 5</note> but this Spirit
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41226:7"/>is quite the contrary, paſſionate, furious, irreconcileable implacable; and its Works are, Emulation, Envy, Strife, Anger, Malice, Hatred, Rage, Revenge, and the like. So that in thoſe Words of the Dr. to the Houſe of Commons, [<hi>Though I muſt not ſay with St.</hi> Paul,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>rm. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>g. 25.</note> 
               <hi>that I think I have the Spirit of God; yet I dare ſay that I have the Spirit of that Church in which I was born and bred; and I dare ſay no more:</hi>] there may be more truth than he was aware of, or did intend. And if the Apoſtles in their Zeal for Chriſt himſelf knew not what Spirit they were of, it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if this Faction be of another Spirit than that which is of God, though they may not know it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As it is plain that this Spirit of the Faction is not the Spirit which is of God, ſo it is as plain that it is the Spirit of the World, by the great Fervour and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction it hath and produceth to the things of the World, and the little concern it hath for the things of God: Great Zeal and Jealouſie for the External Pomp and Grandeur of the Church, and the Honour and Dignity of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy; but little concern for the Internal Beauty and Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of the Church, or for the Honour of God or the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion: As our Saviour ſaith, <hi>No Man can ſerve two Maſters; for either he will hate the one and love the other, or elſe he will hold to the one, and deſpiſe the other: Ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſerve God and Mammen:</hi> So it is plain, that the reaſon why they have ſo little concern for the Honour and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, is becauſe they are ſo full of the Spirit of the World: There is their Treaſure, and there are their Hearts alſo. This is apparent in many and frequent Inſtances of divers Natures; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting of former, and many times great Charges, for a little advantage of Profit; Deſerting of ſuch Charges as an induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Man might well enough diſcharge, and for Advantage in the Profits not only accepting but contending for ſuch Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as are greater than they can poſſibly diſcharge. And for <hi>Pluralities</hi> and <hi>Non-reſidence</hi> I refer the Reader to Mr. <hi>Jones</hi>'s Sermon, and to the <hi>Groans of the Church,</hi> in a Book entituled <hi>Icha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bod,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Harris</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:41226:7"/>
            <p> And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is as plain, that there is more in it than meerly the ſordid Spirit of the World, the Spirit of Covetouſneſs, though that be ſaid to be Idolatry, (as is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry excurſion of the Affections to any thing more than to God;) and the amity of the World to be enmity to God, there is alſo a proud, haughty, arrogant, domineering Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Oppoſition, of whatever ſtands in its way, of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, of any thing, tho' never ſo neceſſary; of the very ſpirit and life of Religion, and of Chriſt himſelf in his Saints: In plain terms, the Spirit of Antichriſt, the very ſame with that of <hi>Rome,</hi> only a little reſtrained by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation from ſome particular Projects of Oppoſition, which yet it ſupplies by others as effectual. But in divers Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces it appears to be the very ſame: As,
<list>
                  <item>1. In <hi>violent Oppoſition of any Reformation,</hi> though never ſo reaſonable, or neceſſary, and upon the very ſame Principles, <hi>viz.</hi> leaſt it ſhould weaken their Authority, or abridge ſome Temporal Advantage. And hence it is that not any of thoſe things, which the firſt Reformers ſettled as well as they could for the preſent, but noted to be defective, and deſired might be more compleatly reformed in due time, hath to this day bin promoted toward a more compleat Reformation; but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever appear'd much concerned for it, were oppoſed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached and perſecuted. As this appeared early, even in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time; when thoſe who deſired a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in reſpect of Diſcipline, were at firſt reproached with the Name of <hi>Diſciplinarians,</hi> and afterwards perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted unto Death, not without ſome ſtraining of the Law againſt them, but not any thing done in ſo neceſſary a Caſe. The very ſame Spirit it is, which in the caſe of <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities, and Non-Reſidence,</hi> that ſtorms and bandies againſt <hi>David Jones,</hi> for but touching upon it in <hi>tranſitu.</hi> And the ſame Wicked Spirit it is, which keeps our Diviſions, not only by Obſtinacy againſt all Chriſtian Condeſcention in things indifferent, leaſt they ſhould remit any thing of their Authority; but by obtruding new occaſions of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41226:8"/>and Difference, to keep out as many as they can from Conformity, that ſo they may ingroſs all Preferments the more intirely to themſelves.</item>
                  <item>2. In <hi>more ſtrictly requiring Obedience and Conformity to their own Laws, than to the Laws and Commands of God;</hi> nay, at the ſame time permitting the greateſt Violations and Contempt of the Goſpel by their own Members without the leaſt reſentment, and conniving at notorious Immoralities, I might ſay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulging them, in ſuch as are but zealous for the Church, as they call the Faction; for ſuch are frequently excuſed, treated and commended by them as honeſt Loyal Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, though they ſeldom appear at the Church, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form any ſerious act of Religion. And what is this but ſetting up themſelves above the Worſhip of God?</item>
                  <item>3. In <hi>flattering and cajoling of Princes:</hi> or in the Scripture phraſe, in <hi>Fornication with the Kings of the Earth.</hi> There is only this <hi>Difference between the Great Whore and this Faction,</hi> that the former, like a great Perſon, a ſtately Dame, was folicited and courted by the Kings of the Earth, and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly commanded them, though ſhe proſtituted her ſelf to their embraces: But this, like a little Whore, or Common Proſtitute, ſolicited them, and mercenarily proſtituted her ſelf to their Pleaſure for Silk Stockings, Ribbons, and ſuch Finery, for Preferments. But in three moſt material things they agree exactly. 1. In aſſerting the Pretences of their Gallants. 2. In raiſing themſelves in Temporal Advantages by them. 3. In incenſing them to eſpouſe their Quarrels, and by Temporal Laws, and Civil and Military Power to ſubdue or ſuppreſs their Adverſaries. But this muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, and the Myſtery be made manifeſt.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Sacred Office</hi> of Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, I think truly the moſt Honourable Employment that a mortal Man is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of; and therefore ſhould think nothing too much for them, which might render the Perſons employed in ſuch an Office the more honourable in the ſight of all Men. But when I conſider, what only is truly <hi>Honourable</hi> in the ſight
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41226:8"/>of God, of the Bleſſed Angels, and of all wiſe men; and what is ſo only in the Opinion of the Ignorant People of the World; that theſe latter without the former are apt rather to move Indignation and Contempt, than any truly honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Eſteem in the Minds of Men; and that Common Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſheweth, that ſuch is the corruption of Humane Nature, that they not only uſually prove Lures to corrupt minds, to attract ſuch as to the Prey, but for the moſt part corrupt or debaſe even the better ſort of thoſe who do but accept them; it puts me in mind of that notable Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus,</hi> concerning the Biſhops of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Countrey Biſhops; That the former indeed lived in great Splendor, rode in their Coaches, were curiouſly cloathed, and fared ſumptuouſly; but might be truly happy, if deſpiſing the Grandure of the City they liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like the latter, whom their modeſt Attire, their ſpare Dyet, and their humble Behaviour, recommended both to the Eternal Deity, and to the ſincere Worſhippers of him. It makes me think alſo of the words of that Great and Good Man, Sir <hi>Matthew Hale,</hi> who, when I told him the News of the Preferment of one of the Clergy, whom I knew he had a reſpect for, replyed very ſeriouſly and gravely: <hi>I did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver rejoyce in the Preferment of any of my Friends of the Clergy; for though it be a good ſign of good times when Good Men are preferred; yet I do not think it good for them: For I never knew any man made better by Preferments, but many worſe.</hi> And it makes me conclude with much Aſſuranee of Truth, that thoſe things wherewith <hi>Conſtantine</hi> heretofore, and our Anceſtors in this Nation afterward, expreſſed much Affection and Reſpect to the Church, and piouſly deſigned to adorn and exalt it in Eſteem, Honour and Power, have proved in truth no better than the unadviſed Indulgences of fond Parents uſually prove to their Children; pleaſe their childiſh Affections for the preſent, but inſenſibly deprave both Body and Mind, and deprive them of many real and great Advantages, which a prudent Diſcipline, and well regulated Education would
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41226:9"/>have furniſhed them with. Certain it is, that the admired things of the World do not ſatisfie, but Dropſie-like increaſe the Thirſt, and ſo intangle Mens Minds more and more in worldly Affections, which the deſign of Chriſtianity is to diveſt us of. The genuine <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> is the moſt Divine and only compleat Philoſophy, that ever appeared among Men. And a <hi>true Church of Chriſt</hi> is a Society of Men ſelect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the World, not corporally, but in their Souls and Affections, and certain Inſtitutions and Manners; and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly amongſt others, by Renunciation of the Pomps and Vanities of it. Such a Church debauch'd by the Spirit of the World, becomes a <hi>Whore</hi> in a ſpiritual ſenſe, according to the phraſe of the S. Scriptures. And when the luſt of thoſe things is excited by this Spirit of the World, to the Rage of Perſecution of the Members of Chriſt, it becomes then a compleat <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the Great and Famous <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> the Miſtreſs of all the Weſtern Churches, being debauch'd, became the <hi>Great Whore;</hi> and the reſt were only as Servants to her, or Members of her. And ſuch was <hi>the Church of England,</hi> till ſhe deſerted her Service at the Reformation, and ſet up for her ſelf. Then indeed ſhe began to reform many of the Corruptions of her Miſtreſs; but her <hi>State and Grandeur</hi> ſhe thought ſhe might retain without Detriment or Danger to her Integrity, little ſuſpecting that this was the Root and principal Occaſion of all the Corruptions of that once famous and truly honourable Church; and the more eaſily over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looking the Corruptions of which, much of that State and Grandure doth conſiſt, though it be very plain and obvious if duly conſidered: For it is plain, beyond all contradiction, that <hi>our Epiſcopacy,</hi> as it ſtands modelled to this day, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we magnifie our Church upon it, even to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>churching of almoſt all others, is no genuine Inſtitution, but a Mungrel Conſtitution of Antichiſtian Original; and of very pernicious Conſequence both to Church and State. It is a truth, which at leaſt after divers more gentle Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41226:9"/>I muſt ſpeak out: for I ſee no hopes of any good from it, unleſs the Corruptions thereof be reformed. A principal part of what is reputed peculiar to the Epiſcopal Office, is taken from our <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and committed to Laymen, <hi>viz.</hi> The Adminiſtration of <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> This as a piece of State, in imitation of the Grandees of the World, was here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore committed to the Chancellors, as a matter below their Dignity to execute themſelves; ſo that to this day they remain deprived in effect of a conſiderable part of their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: of which Biſhop <hi>Beadle</hi> had ſo juſt a reſentment, that he endeavoured the reſtititution thereof. And as their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in part is taken from them, ſo they on the other ſide are not a little taken from their Office, by <hi>Secular Buſineſs</hi> in Parliament, beſides other Secular Buſineſs in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. Which to me ſeems a greater piece of <hi>Sacriledge</hi> than the alienation of part of their Revenues, and application of it to ſecular uſes. Being thus in part deprived of their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and in part abſtracted from it, it is but agreeable to the reſt, that they are partly alſo deprived of <hi>their Churches.</hi> Where they have Seats indeed left them, but the <hi>Cathedrals</hi> in all or moſt places, if I miſtake not, are not in the Power of the Biſhop, but of the <hi>Dean and Chapter,</hi> conſiſting of a number of Prebends, who are obliged to be reſident ſome certain, but no long time, as three weeks or a month in the Year; and having Cures remote, and commonly out of the Dioceſs, are of little Uſe or Benefit to the Church or City, if at all to any part of the Dioceſs. Thus is the ancient venerable Body or Society of the Biſhop and his Presbytery with us divided and diſtracted, and rendred in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure uſeleſs and inſignificant to the Ends of its Original In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; and the Damage thereof to the Church not only covered and concealed, but augmented alſo, by the Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſecular Titles and Employments, through the ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that Wicked ſpirit. A plain Mungrel Conſtitution, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the ancient ſimple Chriſtian Form.</p>
            <p>That theſe things are not of <hi>Chriſtian Inſtitution,</hi> is plain
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41226:10"/>from the Sacred Scriptures, and the Writings of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of all former Ages before they were introduced. And that they are of <hi>Antichriſtian Original,</hi> is as plain from the Writings of thoſe Ages when they were introduced; but both may be made manifeſt to all Men by a much ſhorter and eaſier way: And that is, by conſidering the different Ends and Deſigns of the Spirit of Chriſt, and of the Spirit of Antichriſt, and the Tendency and Subſerviency of theſe things to the End and Deſigns of the one or the other.</p>
            <p>The <hi>End and Deſign of Chriſt, and of his Spirit,</hi> which doth animate and guide all true Chriſtians, is to withdraw Men from the World, to train and exerciſe them to an entire Subjection of the whole Man to God, and to exalt and unite them, who are dependant Beings, to him, who is their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Center of Repoſe and Happineſs. On the contrary, the <hi>Aim and Deſign of the Wicked One,</hi> the Spirit of Antichriſt, called alſo the <hi>God of this World,</hi> is to withhold and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the Minds of Men from God; and in order thereunto to intangle their Affections with the falſe appearances of the things of this World, and diſtract their thoughts with multiplicity of Superfluities and Impertinences thereof; that being unhinged from their proper Centre, they may center upon ſome falſe bottom, and ſet up themſelves for little Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>Gerentes ſe pro Centro mundi;</hi> which being the very ſtate of the Devils, doth neceſſarily involve them in their Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and engage them to their Party, amongſt whom they muſt unavoidably be ſubject to ſuch as are more powerful than themſelves.</p>
            <p>Accordingly <hi>our Saviour,</hi> when he was pleaſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with Men in the habit of a mortal man, was pleaſed to appear in a mean <hi>Condition,</hi> without Houſe or Lands, without other <hi>Attendants</hi> than his Diſciples, and thoſe cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen out of the meaneſt ſort of people: His <hi>Speeches and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes</hi> weighty and comprehenſive, but plain, and without any affectation either of Oratory or exactneſs of Method: his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions</hi> for Initiation and Confederation of his Diſciples,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41226:10"/>and Worſhip of God, few and ſimple, with little Ceremony, though very ſignificant: His <hi>Doctrines</hi> few and plain, that he was the Son of God, the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> or <hi>Chriſt,</hi> anointed by his Spirit to be a Prince and a Saviour to all Nations; and that of his Fulneſs of the Divine Spirit, we all who believe in him and obey him, ſhould receive, and ſo be partakers of the Divine Nature: His <hi>Precepts</hi> likewiſe few, but very exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, and eaſily intelligible; to love God with all our Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Faculties; and our Neighbour, who is equally rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God, as our ſelves; and to keep our ſelves pure and unſpotted of the World. And accordingly his <hi>Apostles and Diſciples,</hi> thoſe who had not the things of the World, ſought them not, but were contented with Food and Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that they often ſought by their own labours, and thoſe who had more, diſtributed what they had to ſuch as wanted. On the contrary, <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the Scripture, 1. With great Pomp, State, Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, Power and Dominion. 2. With much Subtilty, and ſtrong Deluſions. 3. With great Violence and Cruelty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drunk with the Blood of the Saints. And if we well conſider the <hi>Methods</hi> which have been uſed for the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Chriſtian Religion, through the Inſtigation of that Wicked Spirit, which rules in the Hearts of all wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men, and too often prevails in ſuch as are not of his party, if not well purified from carnal and terrene Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and very vigilant and circumſpect, we ſhall find that the firſt was indeed by open <hi>Violence,</hi> by the Jews and the Heathens: But as ſoon as that appeared not to be ſufficient for his purpoſe, he made uſe of his <hi>Subtilty,</hi> and transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf into an Angel of Light, ſet to work by his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to corrupt the ſimblicity of the Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine with ſubtile Notions, and under pretence of Zeal for the true Faith to raiſe Diſſentions, and divide the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans into different parties, and ſet them one againſt another. And by this Means he prevailed mightily among the <hi>Greeks,</hi> who were addicted to Speculation and Oratory: But when
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41226:11"/>his firſt Method of Force wholly failed him, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours became Chriſtians, neither had his ſecond Method that effect among the <hi>Romans</hi> as it had with the <hi>Greeks,</hi> they being more addicted to <hi>Pomp, and Grandure, and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> than to Notions and Speculations; he preſently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tach'd them with thoſe things which were more agreeable to their Diſpoſition, and inſtigated them to expreſs their Zeal for the Church, by conferring as much of this kind upon it as might be, and their Biſhops as greedily to catch at it. This is that which St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and the Biſhops of that famous Council in <hi>Africa</hi> noted, and gravely and ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reproved in the then Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> that they intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced <hi>Typhum Seculi in Eccleſiam,</hi> the Pomp and Grandure of the World into the Church: And when they were once tainted and levened with this Poyſon of the Spirit of the World, they were eaſily inſtigated to the uſe of Force and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence againſt any who never ſo juſtly oppoſed their Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (as that Council did) till at laſt they proceeded to Blood and all kind of Cruelty in after Ages.</p>
            <p>And now for the <hi>Tendence and Subſervience of theſe things of the World,</hi> ſo much neglected by Chriſt and his true Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and ſo greedily ſought after by others, to which of the Ends before mentioned it is moſt, and the Effects and Conſequences of them upon Men: 1. It is plain that they do for the moſt part ſtrangely inſinuate themſelves into the Affections of thoſe that acquire them; inſomuch that what is commonly ſaid of one of them, <hi>Creſcit amor nummi quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ipſa pecunia creſcit,</hi> may truly be ſaid of all; much would have more, and the more men have, the more they ſtill crave; and ſo eaſily obſervable every where, that I need ſay no more. 2. Theſe Affections to the things of the World are apt continually to occupy and take up the Mind, and to avert it or detain it from God, its proper Object; partly by Complacency in them, and partly by Diſtractions about them. 3. And this doth eaſily proceed to a kind of Truſt and Confidence in them, and Reliance upon them, with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41226:11"/>Acquieſcence and Repoſe; whereby they become ſuch a falſe bottom to it as I mentioned before, an Idol inſtead of the Living God. 4. And this muſt needs partly chill, if not extinguiſh all true Devotion and Affection to God, and cauſe a Narrowneſs of Soul, as to any generous Acts for his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or the common Good of Men; and partly infatuate it with Falſe Security and Preſumption of the Favour of God, grounded upon ſuch External Bleſſings, and a formal outſide Religion according to its own Diſpoſition. 5. And then laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, All is ſoon compleated with that height of Pride, Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, and Indignation and Severity againſt all who oppoſe, or refuſe to ſtoop and pay Reverence to ſo Worſhipful a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. All which is directly contrary to the intire Subjection of the Creature to the Creator, which is the very End of our living here upon Earth, and of the Conduct of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Spirit, and inſenſibly leads into the State, and ſubjects it to the Power of the Devils.</p>
            <p>And for the <hi>Effect and Conſequence thereof upon others,</hi> the <hi>Oſtentation</hi> of thoſe who have ſome ſhare of theſe things, is apt to provoke the <hi>Emulation</hi> of thoſe who have leſs: and that inſtigates them firſt to Care and Pains to get as much as their Neighbours, though otherwiſe they may perhaps have enough for themſelves and their Families, if they would but conform to it; and ſo robs them of much precious Time, and diſtracts their Minds from their proper Object, by unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Care for Superfluities; and ſo alſo gives advantage to the Spirit of the World to inſinuate the deeper into them: And Secondly, if honeſt Pains and honeſt Gains will not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the Emulation, it inſtigates further to indirect Means, as Frauds, Cheats, Exactions, Oppreſſions, ſecret Stealth and open Robbery, wherewith particular Perſons are wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and moleſted, and many undone; many Arts, Projects and Practices of Covetous and Ambitious Officers, Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Stateſmen, and Princes, whereby States and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and whole Nations are diſturbed, and often involved in great Troubles; and moſt of that various Wickedneſs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41226:12"/>which we daily ſee puniſhed with the untimely Death of ſo many Malefactors. But beſides thoſe groſſer Evils, which are apparent to every ordinary Obſervation, there is <hi>another more ſubtile Evil Conſequence,</hi> which falls heavy upon a great part of Mankind, and ſo makes the <hi>Curſe</hi> much <hi>worſe</hi> than ever God made it. It keeps down many Young and many honeſt induſtrious People, that with all their Care, Labour and Induſtry, they are hardly able to get an honeſt Liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and Subſiſtence for their Families, and makes Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a great Temptation to many. Theſe are great Evils un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun, ſuch as do greatly ſtrengthen and increaſe the Kingdom of Darkneſs, and ſuch as the Chriſtians of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches (as we call them) have much to anſwer for before God. But it would require a longer Diſcourſe than is fit for this place fully to explain them. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore only add, that the Great Inſtruments of this Myſtery of Wickedneſs, are the Great Men of the World, the State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Dames, and all that either proſecute the things of the World with Greedineſs, and without meaſure, retain them without uſe, or uſe them with Oſtentation, in Attire, in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſt Faſhions, (ſuch as our Womens <hi>Fioccoes,</hi> fitter for Fore-horſes heads than for the Foreheads of Chriſtian Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,) in great Tables, Curious Furniture, Attendants, and Prodigality at Inns and Taverns, to Servants, upon their Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and other matters, forgetting the Account they muſt one day make for theſe Talents. But no greater Inſtruments do I know in this Myſtery than ſuch <hi>Clergymen,</hi> as forgetting the Deſign and Precepts of the Goſpel, and the Example of our Saviour and the ancient Chriſtians, by a contrary Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in ſeeking Preferments, in making Proviſion for the fleſh, and Oſtentation of the things of the World in themſelves, their Wives and Children, and by too cloſe following, and thereby authorizing and encouraging the Faſhions, and Modes and Finery and State of the World, render themſelves the Devils Journeymen to expoſe and recommend his Wares, and his Servants to ſpread his Snares, who ſhould as the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41226:12"/>and Servants of Jeſus Chriſt by their Example re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend the noble Simplicity of our Chriſtian Profeſſion, as well as by their Doctrine inculcate the Exactneſs of a true Chriſtian Converſation, and the Strictneſs of the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count we muſt all one day give of what we have done in the Fleſh. And yet ſome there are, who, as if their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance and Encouragement to theſe things by their Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were not enough, ſcruple not to be Advocates for them, even in their Pulpits, and in Printed Books, and teach Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by Phariſaical Gloſſes to elude the plaineſt and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Texts of Scripture, and inſtead of Religious care to conform their Manners to them, to ſtudy and invent ſuch Comments for them as may leaſt thwart their corrupt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; little conſidering that the Precepts of the Goſpel were deſigned for Mankind with reſpect to a Common Good, and that many things, which conſidered in themſelves, or as the acts of a particular Perſon, may ſeem little, yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered with all their Circumſtances and Conſequences when become Common to a whole Nation, or to many Nations, are very pernicious, and therefore all participation in them dangerous to particular Perſons. Nor do I ſee how the <hi>Pompous Titles and Veſtments</hi> of our Biſhops can be excuſed from recommending theſe falſe Wares, inſtead of the genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine Ornaments of the Goſpel, as Motives of Reſpect. And certain it is, that thoſe Biſhops, who in the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, were the Principal Reformers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> thought them fit to be reformed; nor was that oppoſed upon any conſideration of Religion, but reaſon of State, and that not well conſidered, as the event hath proved. And I my ſelf have diſcourſed with Biſhops now living, who have expreſſed to me the ſame ſenſe of theſe things, and I doubt not but would willingly conſent to a reformation of them. But for their <hi>Revenues,</hi> I ſhould not wiſh any abatement thereof, provided they were but conferred in ſuch manner as might not continually fill and peſter the Church with worldly Factious Men, and ſo uſed as they ought to be, as Talents whereof an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41226:13"/>muſt be given for the real Service of Religion; that they who have Riches, were as rich in Good Works; that ſo the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might be taught by their Example, as well as by their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, the true Uſe and Value of Temporal things, and the danger of Riches otherwiſe. Only whereas in the firſt Ages, the Stock and Revenues of the Church were imployed partly for the Maintenance of the Biſhop and Clergy in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, not of the Biſhop alone, and partly for Works of Charity, (for ſuch was then the Frugality and Piety of the Clergy, that their Charity often extended to very remote parts,) and whereas afterwards our Anceſtors in this Nation (to ſay nothing of other Parts) ſo ordered the Matter, that beſides an ample ſeparate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue for the Biſhop, all Pariſhes had a competent Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the inferiour Clergy belonging to them; and it was one of the notorious Abuſes of the Papacy to rob the richer Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes of their maintenance for their own Clergy, and therewith augment the Revenues of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or of the <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> which was the Original of <hi>Impropriations;</hi> I do not ſee how our Biſhops and Deans, and Chapters can with good Conſcience retain ſuch Impropriations, and ſee the Pariſhes out of which they receive ſuch Revenues, deprived of competent Maintenance for able Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, or enjoy ſo ample Revenues, as many of them do, and make ſo little uſe of it for the promotion of Chriſtianity either abroad or at home; contrary to the conſtant Doctrine of the Chriſtians of all former Ages, that a Clergyman may not uſe the Stock of the Church, or the Revenues of his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, but only as his Moderate need requires, and is obliged to employ the reſidue in Pious Uſes; and of the Caſuiſts and Doctors of later Ages generally agreeing it to be a Sin in a Clergyman to miſpend what exceeds his moderate Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, and many to be ſuch a Sin, as obligeth to Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the Service of the Church, and Religion: Which ſavours much of the genuine Chriſtian Spirit.</p>
            <p>But this Faction is of a contrary, or quite other Spirit: They have little zeal for, or ſenſe of any pious Uſes. Great Zealotes they are indeed for the Church, but it is but for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41226:13"/>the Pomp and Grandure of it, which conſumes all, and can ſpare nothing for any truly pious Uſes; and like the <hi>Capernaites</hi> who followed Chriſt for the Loaves, only for the Preferments, of which they hope for a ſhare. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is that their Zeal and Jealouſie is very warm againſt Diſſenters, whom they look upon as their Rivals, or their Adverſaries, be they never ſo ſober, ſo Religious, and ſo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious for promoting of Piety and Vertue; but againſt the moſt Profane Contemners of all Religion, if they but favour the Faction, nothing at all. And no leſs Zealots for the State and Government, under the ſpecious Name of Loyalty: But it is in truth only for the obtaining the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, which are not to be had without favour at Court. And therefore they can eaſily be content to ſacrifice the Rights of their Countrey for their own Preferment, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray their Truſt for Penſions and Gratuities; and their Kings too, by baſe Compliances, and by evil and pernicious Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, into ſuch Courſes, as make their Government no leſs uneaſie to themſelves, than to the People; and after all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert them when they ſee occaſion to ſave themſelves, if they have not before made their own caſe deſperate. A juſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment I confeſs for ſuch Princes as will not conſider or be perſwaded in time, that they who will betray their Country to gratifie them, will not fail to betray them alſo for their own Advantage, and to deſert them in caſe of greateſt Danger.</p>
            <p>This plainly is the property of a deceitful Harlot, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Duty and Qualities of a truly loving and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Wife: And if we enquire into <hi>the Original of theſe Amours,</hi> it will be eaſie to trace them to the very beginning and firſt entrance of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Race into this Kingdom King <hi>James</hi> his Heart was undoubtedly (as is uſual in ſuch caſes) mightily lifted up with his ſo eaſie acceſs to the Crown of <hi>England.</hi> And it no leſs filled the Hearts of others with <hi>Hopes and Expectations,</hi> ſome of Honours, ſome of Places and Eſtates, and ſome of both: which his Prodigality of both,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41226:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:41226:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:41226:15"/>yet more inlarged, and Emulation raiſed to the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. Theſe Emulations were partly National between the <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and partly among the <hi>Engliſh</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and thoſe of two ſorts, ſuch as at the Court ſought Preferment in the State, and ſuch as ſought either Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Church, or Favour in Church matters: So that he was addreſſed to, and courted by all Parties for his Favour, in an extraordinary manner, and by moſt in the uſual methods of Courtſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> Magnifying his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and his State and Power beyond Truth and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, inſinuating into him all the Prejudice that might be againſt thoſe who were looked upon as Rivals; and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending their own ſpecious Services, by miſrepreſenting the Modeſty of others for want of affection. And ſo groſs, notorious and impudent were the Acts of this Courtſhip, as provoked the Houſe of Commons in the very firſt Parliament, to make a Declaration of their Grief <hi>to find his Majeſty, to the extream prejudice of his Subjects of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, ſo greatly wronged by Miſinformation;</hi> and among other things concerning the Rights and Liberties of his Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> and the Priviledges of Parliament, which they there aſſert, but belong not to this place to be here recited.</p>
            <p>Among the Competitors for his Favour were many ſerious religious people, who ſought his Favour only for the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of ſome things in the Church, which were thought not ſo throughly reformed as was to be wiſhed. And for that purpoſe prepared a Petition which was ſubſcribed by many hundred hands: They had encouraged themſelves upon the Favour the King had formerly ſhewed them, in writing to the Queen on their behalf; and they had had an Agent with him immediately upon the Queens death, to whom without doubt he gave a fair and ſmooth Anſwer. But ſome of the Biſhops were not behind hand with them in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſoon outwent them in the Succeſs of their Courtſhip and his Favour after he came into <hi>England.</hi> He
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41226:15"/>had conceived a Prejudice againſt a <hi>Scotch Presbytery</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: This <hi>Bancroft</hi> and ſome other hot men took advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of, both to heighten the prejudice againſt all who deſired any thing of a Reformation here, and to inſinuate themſelves into his Favour. And when he found himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and ſecurely ſettled in the Throne beyond his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, he ſoon diſcover'd his Inclinations; and more particularly in his <hi>Proclamation,</hi> 24 Oct. 1603. <hi>Concerning ſuch as ſeek Reformation in Church matters:</hi> Which ſtopp'd the Petition for ſome time; and in the <hi>Conference at Hampton-Court,</hi> 14 <hi>Jan.</hi> which whether appointed at the inſtance of any others, or at the Kings own pleaſure, is uncertain; but ſerved, as appears by the Relation, principally for the King to expreſs his Favour to the Biſhops, and Conforming party, and his Prejudice againſt the reſt, and for them to expreſs their Reſpects to him, as ſome of them did by ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him upon the knee, (viz. <hi>Whitgift</hi> and <hi>Bancroft,</hi>) and applauding what he ſaid, as undoubtedly ſpoken by the ſpecial aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit; and for mutual Courtſhip and Indearments between them.</p>
            <p>But though they were never ſo well aſſured of the Kings Favour, yet were they fearful of the Parliament, which had often in the Queens Time been upon Bills againſt Plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and for Reformation of other matters, which though the Archbiſhop by the Queens means had prevailed to have ſtopped, yet was he ſo concerned, that he wiſhed he might not live to ſee another Parliament. And this diſpoſed Them, not only by way of Complement, as a means to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend themſelves to the King, but in good earneſt for their own Intereſt, being well aſſured of his Favour, to magnifie the Kings Authority, and ſet it as high as might be, even without the concurrence of the Parliament, and to dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate as much as they durſt from their Authority. And this again ſo much the more diſpoſed the King to favour Them, not politickly in apperance only, but in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, as the moſt apt Inſtruments he could have for his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41226:16"/>Deſigns, (which appear by many plain inſtances to have been from his firſt coming in to ſet up himſelf by his Arts and Kingcraft above all Law;) and for that end, to confirm and enlarge the Authority of the Biſhops and Clergy, which depended upon him for their Preferment, as much as might be, to make them the more capable to ſerve his turn.</p>
            <p>And theſe are the true Principles, which have produced and raiſed this Faction to what it is: For upon theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples were things managed by a ſecret Correſpondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and ſome leading men of the Clergy. Accordingly in the next Convocation, after they had provided in the firſt <hi>Cannon</hi> for aſſerting his Supremacy according to the Law of the Land againſt all forreign Juriſdiction, in the next <hi>Canon</hi> they ſet it up paramount the Law, and without the Parliament, to be <hi>the ſame Authority in Cauſes Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, that the godly Kings had among the Jews, and Chriſtian Emperours in the Primitive Church;</hi> and might with as much reaſon have aſſerted as much concerning his Authority in Civil matters if they durſt, for both depend upon the ſame Principles; but that both he and they knew very well would never have paſſed without being taken notice of, and que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion'd in Parliament.</p>
            <p>And therefore there was another Project to help that out, carried on with great Artifice and Secrecy in the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, which at laſt hath appeared in print, publiſhed by the late Archbiſhop, under the Title of <hi>Biſhop Overals Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation Book</hi> (though he was no Biſhop in ſeven years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it paſs'd the Convocation,) The chief purpoſe of which is pretended to be, <hi>to imitate the Scriptures in ſetting out and deſcribing the Dignity of our Saviour Chriſt by his Almighty Power and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Government of all the World,</hi> as they ſay in the beginning. But they tell us not what Occaſion they had to do this in ſo ſolemn a manner. The King in his Letter (lately publiſhed) to good Dr. <hi>Abbot</hi> (who probably was not acquainted with the Intreigue,) tells them, <hi>You know all of you, as I think, that my Reaſon of calling you together, was to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41226:16"/>give your Judgments: How far a Chriſtian and a Proteſtant King may concur to aſſiſt his Neighbours to ſhake off their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their own Soveraign, upon the account of Oppreſſion, Tyranny, or what elſe you like to name it?</hi> Nor does there appear any juſt Occaſion for this: For if it be well conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it was not War, but a Treaty of Peace between the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> which was then under conſideration. Nor does the Form of the Book ſuit with a meer Reſolution of ſuch a Doubt: For it is one thing to give a Judgment or Opinion of a Caſe of Conſcience, and another to make Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons and Decrees. Nor laſtly, is the matter of it propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable only to ſuch an Occaſion. And therefore if the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Form of the Book be well conſidered, there will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear great reaſon to believe that theſe were meer Pretences to cover ſome other Deſign; and that <hi>the true Deſign of the Book</hi> was only or principally to aſſert, That an Abſolute, Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtible and Unaccountable Monarchy, without conſent of the People, is <hi>Jure Divine,</hi> Gods Ordinance, Originally deſcending from him, and depending upon him; and that all others are degenerate Forms of Government; and to aſſert a like <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> for their own Eccleſiaſtical Government, and withall to prejudice, vilifie and decry all Claim of any Right in the Government, or of Liberties by the People, with the reproachful Terms, and under the Notion of <hi>Factious Popularity,</hi> which are plainly known to have been the Kings own Sentiments, by whoſe ſpecial Licenſe and Authority they did ſit and conſult. And this is ſo plain and viſible in the Book, that the Learned Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> makes no Scruple to ſpeak it out plainly, that <hi>The princpal Deſign of it is to aſſert the Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtible Authority of Sovereign Princes;</hi> which was as much of it as his Subject led him to ſpeak of; otherwiſe I doubt not but had he had occaſion, he could and would have ſaid as much of the other part of the Deſign, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if this was indeed the Deſign, it was, in my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, eſpecially as it was managed in that clandeſtine
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41226:17"/>and covert way, and with ſuch a Form of Authority, not only unjuſt, but vile and diſhonourable, unbefitting the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of a <hi>King,</hi> or the dignity of a Convocation of <hi>Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and a great abuſe of Religion, to proſtitute the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſo venerable Authority to abuſe People out of their Right; nay, to enchant them as it were to venture their Lives and Fortunes againſt their own Right and Intereſt, as it did by degrees at laſt make them do, beſides many other Miſchiefs it hath produced, and principally upon the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, as is very uſual by the Juſt Judgments of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God. But all this I will endeavour to make plain and manifeſt as briefly as I can, in the ſeveral Particulars fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That King <hi>James</hi> 1. notwithſtanding his many Profeſſions and ſolemn Proteſtations to govern according to Law, did <hi>from the very beginning of his Reign,</hi> ſtudy and employ all his King-craft, <hi>to make himſelf Abſolute,</hi> and get all into his own Power. This is ſo well known, that I need only mention ſome of <hi>his Artifices</hi> and Attempts to that purpoſe, with References to Evidences and Teſtimonies thereof. As,
<list>
                  <item>1. Upon the <hi>Parliament</hi> it ſelf. 1. To reſtrain the Freedom of <hi>Elections</hi> of Knights and Burgeſſes, and the Returns of Members for divers Corporations, as may be perceived by his Proclamation 1 <hi>Jan.</hi> 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> 2. To draw the <hi>Determination of ſuch Elections</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Chancery,</hi> before an Officer of his own, as may be ſeen in the Caſe of Sir <hi>Fr. Goodwyn,</hi> 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> lately publiſhed in <hi>Lex Parliamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</hi> 3. To reſtrain their <hi>Freedom of Debates,</hi> which was complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of in Parliament, with the two preceding, 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> and afterward occaſioned that Remonſtrance, 24. <hi>May,</hi> 8 <hi>Jac.</hi> and at laſt produced that free and generous Proteſtation concerning their Rights in print, in <hi>Wilſon</hi> p. 188. and <hi>Ruſhworth</hi> p. 53. To which, others might be added; which made the Parliament tell him, that in the firſt Parliament of his Reign, the Priviledges of their Houſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Liberties and Stability of the whole Kingdom had been more univerſally and dangerouſly impugned, than ever ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Parliaments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> V. <hi>Journal,</hi> An. 1.</item>
                  <item>2. To make his <hi>Proclamations</hi> paſs for Laws or Edicts, (as they have ſince done in <hi>France</hi>) of which he publiſhed no leſs than <hi>Seventy</hi> in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41226:17"/>the firſt Year of his Reign, and many every year after, till they were printed all together in a Volume, in the form of Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and Books were written for their Authority, and that the Parliament took notice and complained of it. And then he began to cover it as well as he could by another Proclamation, 24 <hi>Sept.</hi> 8 <hi>Jac.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. To <hi>impoſe Taxes</hi> without conſent of Parliament, as appears by the Remonſtrance, 24 <hi>May,</hi> 1610. printed with a learned and neceſſary Argument concerning that matter, and the Benevolence notwithſtanding extorted, <hi>Anno</hi> 1614. v. <hi>Wilſon</hi> p. 78.</item>
                  <item>4. To ſet up Extrajudicial Opinions of Judges for Laws, (<hi>vide</hi> the <hi>Apol.</hi> 1. <hi>Jac.</hi>) and to impoſe upon the Judges to give Judgments in favour of Prerogative contrary to the Laws, and their own Oaths, as may be ſeen in <hi>Franklins</hi> Annals, <hi>Anno</hi> 1616. 14 <hi>Jac.</hi> which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with that noble Caſe of <hi>Cavendiſh</hi> in <hi>Anderſon,</hi> 1 Rep. 152. in the Queens time, the different behaviour of them two and their Judges, will appear very remarkable.</item>
                  <item>5. To <hi>tune the Pulpits,</hi> (as ſome pretend that Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> uſed to phraſe it) and ſet the Clergy on work by Preaching, Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Diſcourſes, to promote his Deſigns by pretence of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Religion, and to make good by colour of Divinity what could not be done by Law, and ſeek Principles for a choſen Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is the matter now in hand. And therefore,</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Second particular is, That there was at that time <hi>a Party of the Clergy,</hi> who (beſides a Court Faction) ſtruck in, joyned and held a ſecret Correſpondence with him for the promoting of theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. This might be obſerved in divers Inſtances precedent to his firſt Parliament; but the Complaints of the Houſe of Commons the very firſt Seſſions, of ſome of the <hi>Higher Clergy</hi> writing a Book a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, even the Parliament ſitting, and <hi>the Inferiour Clergy</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighing againſt them in Pulpits; yea, publiſhing Proteſtations tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Impeachment of their moſt ancient and undoubted Rights, as may be ſeen in the Journal, is ſufficient evidence of it ſelf, and yet will receive farther Confirmation from what follows.</p>
            <p>The third is, <hi>That this Work was an</hi> Arcanum Imperii, <hi>and managed and tranſacted in a ſecret myſterious and diſguiſed manner between them.</hi> This we may ſee plainly by what They pretend to be <hi>Their chief Purpoſe,</hi> and He to be <hi>His Reaſon of calling them together,</hi> that they did agree in this, that each Party did uſe Colours and Pretences: but as it uſually falls out in ſecret Conſpiracies, that all Circumſtances are not provided for, ſo in this their Diſagreement in the Particular, diſcovers that both
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41226:18"/>were but Pretence. This may further be perceived by <hi>the Kings Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to good Dr. Abbot,</hi> publiſhed in the <hi>Obſervator:</hi> For why ſhould he write of that matter to Good Dr. <hi>Abbot,</hi> rather than to Truſty Dr. <hi>Bancroft,</hi> who was Preſident of the Upper Houſe of Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the Province of <hi>Canterbury?</hi> or to <hi>Thornborough</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> who was one of that Convocation, and beſides was thought ſit to be made Preſident for the Province of <hi>York?</hi> or to Learned Dr. <hi>Overall,</hi> who was the perſon employed to draw up the Book, and was beſides Prolocutor of the Lower Houſe? Nay, why was it written at all? Had the King no Conference with any of them? Was not Archbiſhop <hi>Bancroft</hi> a Privy Councellor? And was none of theſe able to declare the Kings pleaſure to the Convocation? And why ſhould his Orders (mentioned in that Letter) to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of the Clergy be ſent by his Solicitor, and he be again em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in that buſineſs to them? Muſt our Solicitor inſtruct our Biſhops and Clergy in matters of Divinity? or muſt the Biſhops and Clergy determine matters of Law, and Right, and Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to the Kings pleaſure, by the Information of his Solicitor? What other probable Reaſon can be conceived for all this, but that there being an <hi>Arcanum Imperii</hi> to be managed with great Policy and Secrecy, under another Pretence, they who were the principal Confidents and Agents for promoting the Secret, muſt not appear openly at all concerned in it; but becauſe ſome body muſt be employed for the King, good Dr. <hi>Abbot,</hi> whom no body would ſuſpect to be privy to any ſuch Intreagues, and the Solicitor, a Man of another profeſſion, muſt be put upon ſome ſervice which might diſguiſe the matter, and help to prevent ſuſpicion of the true Deſign? And this to me is a great Confirmation that it was all Trick and Intreague between the King and ſome leading Men in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation for the purpoſe aforeſaid. But the while I cannot but pity that Good Man, and divers other ſuch of that Convocation, who, if they did not conſent to thoſe things in the Convocation, are abuſed by <hi>Bancroft,</hi> or <hi>Thornborough,</hi> or <hi>Overal;</hi> or if they did, were not leſs abuſed, being drawn into a matter, the bottom of which they did not underſtand, by a vile Conſpiracy and miſchievous Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which hath hitherto been the Bane of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of the State too, and will henceforward be the ſhame of that Convocation to after Ages.</p>
            <p>And from hence we may alſo perceive the true Reaſon, <hi>why</hi> ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table a Work of this Convocation hath been ſo <hi>great a Secret in our Hiſtory,</hi> and ſo little taken notice of for above fourſcore years, till of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41226:18"/>late made publick; and that which may alſo ſerve for a further Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this matter. Some indeed have concluded from the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Dr. <hi>Abbot,</hi> that it was becauſe <hi>the King was diſpleaſed with them, viz.</hi> for a paſſage there mentioned; and though the words mentioned in the Letter are not literally the ſame, as in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Convocation Book, yet in Charity they could ſcarce believe any Alterations made in the Cannons before they were printed. But by the Letter we underſtand that the King was not ſo diſpleaſed but that he promiſed to ſend them his Orders about it by Mr. Solicitor, and bids them <hi>till then</hi> meddle no more with it. And the Publiſher of the Book informs us, that there were ſeveral Amendments made by the Upper Houſe of Convocation, and that the Book was print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to them. And the Sabſcriptions of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and of the Biſhop of <hi>Briſtoll</hi> Preſident of the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>York,</hi> to the firſt Book, ſhew that the Work did afterward go on, was finiſhed, and paſſed not only that Convocation, but that of the Province of <hi>York</hi> alſo: And further than that did they go, even to adde two Books more to it. So that there was no ſuch diſpleaſure of the King againſt it; nor could that be the reaſon why thoſe Canons were never ratified in Parliament, or ſtamped with the Kings Authority. But the moſt probable Reaſon, conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Nature of the thing, and to the Methods which were uſed, is either, That it was <hi>never intended to be publiſhed,</hi> leſt it ſhould be confuted, and ſo the Deſign ſpoil'd, or cenſured in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and ſo turned againſt them, but be kept as a Secret: For ſo its Authority would be no leſs Venerable, nor would its Effects be leſs powerfull upon ſome prime leading men, who might influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence others: Or, That it was <hi>thought fit firſt to try how ſome ſuch Notions vented by private men would paſs or eſcape,</hi> before the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Authority of ſuch a Work ſhould be expoſed to Cenſure. And accordingly ſoon after were divers Books with paſſages in them to the ſame purpoſe publiſhed, of which notice was taken in Parliament, and among the reſt one by <hi>Blackwell</hi> a Secular Prieſt, whom, if I miſtake not, <hi>Bancroft</hi> kept in his Houſe, or protected; and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther written by <hi>John Cowel</hi> Doctor of Law, and dedicated to the Archbiſhop, <hi>(Bancroft,)</hi> who, as he there ſaith, at his coming to him from the Univerſity, firſt put him upon thoſe Studies, and was ſuſpected, as he confeſſed in Parliament, to have a Finger in the Book. And upon this the <hi>Commons</hi> firſt, and afterward <hi>both Houſes,</hi> fell very warmly; till the King ſeeing what they were like to do, to ſave his Champion from more ſevere Cenſure, and to pacifie the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41226:19"/>Parliament, takes upon himſelf to ſuppreſs it, by a Proclamation on purpoſe. And a <hi>Proclamation</hi> indeed came out, but ſuch as ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſhews the Kings Diſpoſition and Tenderneſs in the Caſe. And this was a ſufficient Experiment to ſhew then what was like to become of the Convocation Book ſhould it be offered to the Parliament, authorized by the King, or ſo much as appear in publick: And this may be the reaſon why it was ſo long before any compleat Treatiſe upon thoſe Principles ever appeared. For that, if done by any conſiderable Perſon, might not only have provoked the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Parliament, but have expoſed them to Examination and Diſcuſſion of able Lawyers, and other Learned men both at Home and abroad, (for all Nations are concerned in it,) and that K. <hi>James</hi> and ſome others of that Party had reaſon enough to ſuſpect they would not bear: And therefore we meet with little of them, till Sir <hi>Ro. Filmer</hi>'s <hi>Patriarcha</hi> was publiſhed after his Death, upon the perſwaſion of Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> and after K. <hi>Charles</hi> 2. his Reſtoration, at a very ſeaſonable time for ſuch ſtuff. So that this was ſufficient reaſon why ſo extraordinary a Work as this, which concerns all the Governments of the World, and could not eſcape the Cenſures of all, beſides the Effect it might have in the Parliament and the whole Nation, ſhould be no leſs carefully kept ſecret than we find it to have been, (though that be very ſtrange,) to produce its Effect like ſome Spell or Magical Operation, unperceived, as I ſhall fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther explain it, when I have diſpatched one particular more. And that is,</p>
            <p n="4">4. That this Secret, this Work of Darkneſs, was a Work alſo of Diſhoneſty, <hi>a Hidden Work of Diſhoneſty,</hi> and a Myſtery of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: I might adde, and of kin to the great Myſtery of Iniquity. And to diſpatch this, I ſhall paſs by leſſer matters, and apply my ſelf only to the <hi>Two main Pillars,</hi> upon which all their pretended <hi>Irreſiſtible Power</hi> of all Soveraign Princes depend, which if I do but remove from under their Structure, all their work muſt fall to the Ground. Theſe two Pillars or Principles of their Regal Power, are, the one <hi>Patriarchal,</hi> derived from the Patriarchs; the other <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential,</hi> acquired by the Diſpoſal of the Divine Providence.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>the Patriarchal</hi> they build a <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> for an Abſolute, Irreſiſtible Monarchy, making and calling all other Forms of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Degenerate Forms.</hi> But for a Foundation for this, having no Evidence of any Poſitive Law of God, they are forced to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Law of Nature; and becauſe from thence they could only prove a <hi>Poteſtas Patria,</hi> they would confound that and <hi>Poteſtas
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41226:19"/>Regia;</hi> and that <hi>Poteſtas Patria</hi> is in a ſort <hi>poteſtas Regia,</hi> we muſt believe upon their Authority. Which is right like deceitfull Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to build upon a falſe or uncertain Foundation. But had it bin in truth as they would have us believe, that <hi>Poteſtas Patria</hi> was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort <hi>Regia,</hi> and ſo the Patriarchs were indeed Monarchs, (which they were not, though they were indeed more, <hi>viz.</hi> Lords and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors,) yet, becauſe the Brother hath not by any Law of Nature any ſuch Power or Authority over his Brethren, as the Father hath over his Children, the <hi>Monarchy</hi> after the death of the Patriarch, if he hath divers Children, doth neceſſarily by the Law of Nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it ſelf into an <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> and that again after a Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or two into a <hi>Democracy,</hi> as the ultimate reſult of Nature, where it reſteth as having attained its greateſt Perfection, under the Theocracy of the ſupreme Monarch of the World, and from whence no Monarchy can ever proceed, but either by the expreſs Appointment of God, or by Agreement, Conſent or Act of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or by Violence, which may acquire a Poſſeſſion indeed, but never any Right, <hi>jure naturali.</hi> And a meer Violence without Right, may by the Law of Nature be removed by Force, whenever ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent can be raiſed to do it: So that for any King to diſown any Title by Conſent of the People, unleſs he claim by expreſs Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of Almighty God, is a Diſclaimer of the beſt Title he hath, and a kind or degree of Abdication: And conſequently all who do ſo, are Uſurpers and Tyrants, and may juſtly be depoſed whenever the People pleaſes, and can do it. Beſides, ſince there is no Prince in the World who can claim by this Patriarchal Right, or is poſſeſſed of any ſuch Government, what is to call all other forms <hi>degenerate Forms,</hi> but to affront all the Governments now in the World.</p>
            <p>The other Pillar or Principle of <hi>Providential</hi> Right, which is ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled <hi>Ch.</hi> 28. and the Canon following, is this: <hi>That when Subjects ſhake off their Obedience to their Soveraigns, and ſet up a Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment after their own Humours; or Kings through Ambition and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice invade their Neighbours, they do wickedly: And that the Offences of ſuch Rebels or Oppreſſing Kings are not mitigated by the Providence of God in uſing them: But when any ſuch New Forms of Government, begun by Rebellion, are after throughly ſettled, the Authority in them is of God; and all who live within the Territories of ſuch New Governments, are bound to be ſubject to Gods Authority, which is there executed, and may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt the ſame.</hi> They are their own words, as the Book is printed. But here it was they were at a ſtand, at this <hi>Ch.</hi> and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41226:20"/>
               <hi>Canon.</hi> The King in his Letter before mentioned, calls it a <hi>Thorny Buſineſs</hi> It ſeems he had led, if not drove them into a Labyrinth, out of which neither he nor they knew how to extricate themſelves. So hard it is when Men leave honeſt, plain, and ſimple Truth, to fix upon Pinciples for a choſen Concluſion, and to form any Pillars which can ſupport a falſe and deceitful Building. The King had done beforore what he could in his ſlye way, <hi>quaſi aliud agens.</hi> He had often told his Mind concerning <hi>Jus Regium in ſubditos,</hi> as in <hi>May</hi> laſt (they are his Words in the Letter) in the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Occaſion of <hi>Hales</hi>'s Pamphlet. <q>And Mr. Solicitor, <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> hath ſufficiently expreſs'd my own thoughts concerning the Nature of Kingſhip in general, and concerning the Nature of it, <hi>ut in mea perſona.</hi>
               </q> And yet after all it ſeems he was at a loſs about it, and therefore ſaith, <hi>They are Edg'd tools, or rather like that Weapon that's ſaid to cut with one Edge, and cure with the other,</hi> and hids them med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle no more in it till <hi>He</hi> gives them <hi>His Orders</hi> by Mr. Solicitor. What <hi>His Orders</hi> were we know not yet; but whatever they were, we may perceive them all here plainly intangled, confounded, and inconſiſtent with themſelves, and their Principal Deſign: and ſo as to eſtabliſh and confirm what they deſigned to ſubvert and aboliſh, that is, The Peoples Rights and Intereſt in Government, and that <hi>Jure Divino</hi> as plainly as any Right of Monarchs; and to ſubvert what they deſigned to build or fortifie, <hi>viz.</hi> an eſſential Abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Irreſiſtibility of Monarchy <hi>Jure Divino.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>For, 1. They had been impoſing upon the S. Scriptures, and ſtraining it in the 27. Chapters, and as many Canons preceding, to extort from it ſome appearance of a Divine Preſcript or Appointment of ſuch an Abſolute Irreſiſtible Patriarchal Monarchy, as the only approved Form of Goverment, and for their own Hierarchy ſubject to it; and this under pretence of ſetting out the Deity, Dignity, Almighty Power, and Univerſal Government of our Saviour Chriſt. Which how near of kin it is to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Antichriſtian Impoſture, and how groſs an Act of Spiritual Fornication between them, and what an illegitimate and ſpurions brood was like to be generated by it, I leave to ſuch Readers as have their Senſes exerciſed to judge.</item>
               <item>2. But how to derive this <hi>Patriarchal Right</hi> to all Sovereign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces now, was ſuch a Difficulty as put them to a loſs. By Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Succeſſion they could not: for none can now prove himſelf Heir by Deſcent to any of the Patriarchs; nor can any now prove a Divine Nomination or Appointment of himſelf or any Anceſtor, to whom he can prove himſelf Heir by Deſcent; or any Grant from any
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41226:20"/>ſuch Patriarch or Prince. And to derive any Right from a delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and well conſidered Agreement of a Free People, was contrary to the Deſign; and they had already reſolved and decreed, <hi>Can.</hi> 2. with no little Sophiſtry, <q>That if any man affirm any ſuch thing of a Civil Power and Authority in, or derived from the People, (whom they pleaſe not to name without ſome additional Title of <hi>Diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Multitude,</hi> or <hi>Factious Popularity,</hi>) he doth greatly erre.</q>
               </item>
               <item>3. And therefore having taken all that pains to lead People into a perſwaſion that ſuch an Abſolute, Irreſiſtible Monarchy is <hi>Jure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino,</hi> for an Expedient to ſupply that Defect, and derive this to all Sovereign Princes now <hi>Jure Divino</hi> only, without admitting any Right derived from the People, they contrive this Artifice, to frame this other Pillar, only of the wicked Acts of Uſurpers and Rebels, (as if no others but ſuch were the Authors and Founders of All Governments now in being,) and the Providence of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſing and overruling theſe wicked Acts to his own Deſigns. Which is ſuch a piece of <hi>ſhuffling Diſingenuity,</hi> or rather <hi>Diſhoneſty and Impiety,</hi> as no man of a Chriſtian Spirit will offer to excuſe, but abominate and deteſt; being built upon a falſe Suppoſition, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to many plain Inſtances in <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and divers ancient Hiſtorians, and other Writers of the Original of Governments, of which ſuch Learned men as <hi>Bancroft,</hi> and the principal Managers of that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, could not be ignorant.</item>
               <item>4. But in this, as ſuch Enterprizes uſe to prove, by the ſpecial Judgment of God, their <hi>Folly and Infatuation</hi> appears to be no leſs than their Diſingenuity and Diſhoneſty: For from their Doctrine and Reſolutions will theſe things undenyably <hi>follow, contrary</hi> to their own Deſign, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1. That God hath not determined by any poſitive Law or Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Will in the S. Scripture, any <hi>one Form</hi> of Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for all Nations; but left that to the Determination of his Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Providence, diſpoſing the Nature, and Circumſtances and Minds of People, and interpoſing in their Actions and Counſels to conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute one or other, as ſhould ſeem moſt expedient. And,</item>
               <item>2. That if when any new Form of Government (whatever it be) is throughly ſettled, the <hi>Authority</hi> in it is <hi>of God,</hi> and all are bound to be ſubject to Gods Authority which is there executed; then is the Authority which the People either retain in the Firſt Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Government, or recover afterwards, when throughly ſettled, whether in the making, diſpenſing with, or abrogating Laws, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the Government, or Correcting the Exorbitances of Princes themſelves, or whatever elſe, as much of God, and <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> as the Authority of any King whatever can be.</item>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:41226:21"/>
               <item>3. That if this be true in the Caſe even of ſuch <hi>new Governments</hi> as <hi>began</hi> by ſo unjuſt and wicked means as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations and Rebellions,</hi> as is affirmed and decreed by the Convocation, then muſt it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to be unqueſtionably true in the caſe of all ſuch Governments as began without any ſuch wicked or unjuſt Means, and were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by a <hi>deliberate mutual Agreement of a Free People,</hi> who being <hi>ſui juris,</hi> might and ought, <hi>jure naturali &amp; divino,</hi> to conſider and agree of ſuch a Form of Government as They ſhould judge moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for themſelves.</item>
               <item>4. That if a <hi>Free People</hi> wiſely conſidering the Inconveniences in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to the three ſimple Forms of Government, <hi>conſtitute a Form</hi> of Government for themſelves, ſo compoſed as to comprehend what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is deſirable in any of them, and to avoid the Inconveniences incident to each, as far as their Humane Prudence can diſcern; do this upon great Deliberation, and by <hi>Publick Pact</hi> or Matual Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and ratifie the ſame by <hi>Solemn Oath</hi> of all Parties: Such an Original of Government is according to the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> being a Neceſſary Proviſion, upon Principles of Reaſon and Wiſdom, for the Common Good, without Injury to any; hath the <hi>Obligation of the Law of Nature,</hi> being a Publick Pact by mutual and Deliberate Agreement; hath alſo a <hi>Divine Obligation</hi> by the <hi>Solemn Oath</hi> of the Parties, ſubjecting all to the Judgment of God in a ſpecial manner; and may reaſonably be believed to have been promoted by the ſecret Energy or Providence of God, who is a Lover of Mankind, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ready to aſſiſt them in all Sober, Juſt and Wiſe Counfels; to be <hi>his Ordinance,</hi> and to have <hi>his Authority</hi> in all reſpects in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner: And that the Violation of any part of ſuch a Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, by whomſoever it is, is a Violation of the Ordinance of God, and like to provoke his Judgments upon all who ſhall dare to tranſgreſs ſo many and great Obligations; and moſt ſeverely upon ſuch as ſhall do it with a high hand, let their pretences be what they will.</item>
               <item>5. If in a Government ſo conſtituted, it be agreed more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, that a certain Perſon, being beſt qualified for that purpoſe, for the neceſſary Exerciſe of Government, ſhall be as it were the Principle of motion; and for the greater Honour and Majeſty of the State ſhall have the Title of <hi>King,</hi> and be inveſted with the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Majeſty,</hi> the <hi>Crown and Scepter,</hi> by expreſs conſent of the People firſt ſolemnly asked, but firſt ſhall take a Solemn <hi>Oath at his Coronation</hi> to Govern according to the Laws, before any Subject ſhall ſwear Allegiance to him: ſhall have with thoſe the Jewels and Crown-Lands, and Publick Revenue of the Nation; but to uſe for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41226:21"/>the State and Defence of the Realm, not to alienate at his Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: In the <hi>Adminiſtration of Juſtice,</hi> all Authority, Proceſs, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and Writs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall be in his Name, but ſo as he may not refuſe it to any; the deſignation and authorizing of the Perſons of the Judges, ſhall be by him, but only with ſuch Powers, and for ſuch Judicatures as are conſtituted by Law; and they ſhall be ſworn to Judge and do Juſtice according to Law, ſhall not obey his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or Commands to the contrary; and he himſelf and his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Civil Matters ſhall be ſubject unto and bound by their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: In <hi>Matters of State</hi> all ſhall be by his Authority, but by Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Nobility, or of a Privy Council of Perſons ſworn in due Form of Law, and who ſhall be anſwerable for what Advice they give: Laſtly, As to the <hi>Ardua Regni,</hi> and <hi>Great Matters,</hi> of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, diſpenſing with, and repealing Laws, redreſſing of Grievances, impoſing of Taxes, making of War, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the <hi>Aſſembling of the States</hi> of the Realm ſhall be by him, but within a certain definite time; the <hi>Diſmiſſion</hi> of them likewiſe, but not till all the Buſineſs be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched; the <hi>Ratification of Laws</hi> ſhall be by him, but only of ſuch as are firſt agreed both in Matter and Form by the other States: He may <hi>make War</hi> by Advice of the Privy Council, but at his own Charge, unleſs the other States agree to it; and if it prove preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the Nation, they are to conſider of it: And to them the Impoſing of Taxes, the Examination and Declaration of Grievances, and the Inſpection and Conſideration of the Management, State and Condition of All belongs, as a Right and Power remaining in and retained by them. In ſumm, the Government is ſo conſtituted of all the three Forms, that the <hi>Regal</hi> is plainly but <hi>one third</hi> part of the whole, and that moſt <hi>Honorary, conferr'd</hi> upon him by the reſt, and apparently in all the Parts <hi>in truſt</hi> for the Whole; but moſt of the reſt <hi>Originally</hi> in them, retained by them, and ſo remaining in them, <hi>jure naturali:</hi> This Conſtitution muſt by the Doctrine of this Convocation be confeſſed to be, as it is in truth, <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi> and the Authority which it hath, to be <hi>Gods Authority.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Now ſuch a King is a <hi>Soveraign Prince,</hi> and he is <hi>Abſolute;</hi> that is, he is not bound by any Tenure to any other Emperour, King or State: In this ſence he is both theſe, and his Crown is for the ſame reaſon an <hi>Imperial Crown:</hi> But otherwiſe he is not Abſolute to do what he pleaſeth, that is, without Law, or that <hi>his Will</hi> ſhould be a Law, as the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours was, <hi>Quod Principi placuerit Lex eſto.</hi> He hath ſo much as the Common Agreement or the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath given him, and no more; the other States in all things elſe retaining their Natural Power, and not only the Laws, which
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41226:22"/>he is ſworn to obſerve, confining him within bounds, but the very Conſtitution, which gives him his being: And therefore if a Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ariſe in ſuch a Conſtitution concerning any Right of King or People, the Proof will ly on the part of the King to make good his Claim by the publick Agreement or Conſtitution, and not on the part of the People, who have a precedent Title, viz. <hi>Jure Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turali,</hi> and are ſubject to him in nothing but what he hath by the Conſtitution, or Original Contract.</p>
            <p>And ſuch an intire Conſtitution being <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi> and the Authority reſiding in the whole, and in each part <hi>Gods Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> the Authority of the whole is <hi>Irreſiſtible;</hi> and the Authority of each of the Parts equally Irreſiſtible. And therefore, as whoever violates the Authority of the whole violates Gods Authority, ſo whoever violates the Authority of either of the parts, in that part violates the Authority of the whole, and Gods Authority; and may therefore be reſiſted, though it be either of the Parts that doth it, even the King himſelf: For in that he doth not act by, but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Gods Authority: and <hi>Reſiſtance of the King</hi> in ſuch caſe, is no Reſiſtance of his Authority (for he had no ſuch Authority to do what he doth,) but of a Tyrant, or an Invader, Aggreſſor or Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; nor <hi>Rebellion,</hi> but a Juſt Defence of the Government and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, of Gods Ordinance and Gods Authority. But on the other ſide, as ſuch a <hi>Violation</hi> may be, either by open Force, or by Fraud, ſecret Practice and Conſpiracy, ſo they who do it this way, are as much Traytors againſt the Government, as they are Rebels who do it the other, though againſt the King himſelf. And if the King in ſuch a Conſtitution, conſpire with a part of the People to do this, He and They become thereby, a Trayterous Faction, He violates Gods Ordinance, his own Oath, and in effect Abdicates his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and may juſtly be depoſed for his Trayterous Practice, and They be puniſhed as Betrayers of their Countrey, and Traytors to the Government. And God himſelf doth often puniſh ſuch Abuſes of his Authority, eſpecially in perſons profeſſing Religion, even in this Life by his Providence with very ſevere and <hi>remarkable Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> And ſuch we may obſerve in the preſent buſineſs of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, and the Conſequences thereof, from firſt to laſt, as will further appear in what follows. For,</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, I think it apparent, that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Reſolutions of this Convocation, do, as I ſaid, plainly <hi>confirm what they were deſigned to ſubvert, and ſubvert what they were deſigned to erect or raiſe up;</hi> which is an argument of a very ſtrange Infatuation, as if God had ſmitten them with Aſtoniſhment, given
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41226:22"/>them a Spirit of Slumber, and mingled a <hi>perverſe Spirit</hi> in the midſt of them; as he threatned to do in the Counſels of the <hi>Egyptians, Iſa.</hi> 19. a thing not at all incredible, or indeed to be queſtioned, if we conſider how wicked and perverſe a work it was they were about, which is likewiſe apparent and eaſie to be concluded from what hath been ſaid: that is, in general, as I ſaid before, a hidden Work of Diſhoneſty, and a very Myſtery of Iniquity; but more particularly ſuch a <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> as I mentioned but now, with divers <hi>Aggravating Circumſtances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For that Conſtitution there deſcribed is the very true and genuine <hi>Engliſh Conſtitution,</hi> and one of the beſt in the World. But the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Deſign</hi> of that Book, (as Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> hath rightly obſerved, and is apparent to an ordinary Capacity) and by conſequence of that King, and of the Principal Managers of that Convocation in it, was to aſſert the Irreſiſtible Authority of Soveraign Princes, as he phraſeth it, that is, ſuch an Authority, <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> as makes them irreſiſtible in any thing: Which is utterly inconſiſtent with ſuch a Conſtitution, where the Supreme Authority is ſo divided among ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Eſſential parts, as with us, the King, the Lords, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. So that it was plainly a Conſpiracy againſt the Government of their Country, to enſlave their Country, and turn the Legal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment thereof into Tyranny; againſt an Ancient ſettled Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Countrey, and therefore, according to their own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, againſt the Ordinance of God, and Gods Authority.</p>
            <p>And <hi>their End</hi> in it was plainly for their own Advantage, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame with that of the Papiſts, and generally of aſpiring Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: They are all for Arbitrary Government, not only in pretence to inſinuate themſelves into Favour, but in reality, becauſe they find it more eaſie to deal with the ſingle Perſon of a Prince, and to deceive him with Flatteries and Inſinuations, than with ſo great a Body of Men as an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament, among whom it can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be expected but there will alwayes be ſome or other of Parts and Ability to diſcern and defeat their Projects before they can bring them to perfection, and who will not be corrupted, as Favourites often may. And the Parliament in the Queens time had bin ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten upon Reformation of Pluralities, Non-reſidence, and other matters as ungrateful to them, as before to the Papacy, that they even dreaded the thoughts of it. And this was their Tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Occaſion of their engaging in ſuch a Work, in ſuch a Manner.</p>
            <p>And indeed <hi>the Manner of</hi> their <hi>managing</hi> this Work is no leſs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, being altogether agreeable to a Myſtery of Iniquity, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:41226:23"/>1. Under <hi>Falſe Pretences;</hi> pretence of Religion, and pretence of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out the Dignity of our Saviour Chriſt, by his Almighty Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Univerſal Government of the World; ſo like the Great Myſtery, that never was Daughter more like her Mother. 2. With <hi>groſs Sophiſtry and Fallacies,</hi> craftily leading People into ſuch Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions as they cautiouſly forbear to affirm. As <hi>Can.</hi> 2. concerning the Original of Civil Power, to affirm, <hi>That it was derived from the People,</hi> they ſeem very formally to condemn as a great Error; and yet they craftily intermix ſo many allayes, that indeed they do not, unleſs it be affirmed, 1. As a <hi>Conſequence</hi> of ſuch Premiſes there mentioned as may be in ſome ſort falſe. 2. That it was <hi>firſt</hi> ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived. 3. And not ſimply from the People, but from the People <hi>and diſordered Multitude.</hi> And 4. it muſt alſo be coupled with this Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, <hi>and is not Gods Ordinance,</hi> &amp;c. So that it ſeems a deſigned Artifice to deceive the People, and miſlead them into an Opinion, which yet they themſelves did not believe, and had therefore ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their Evaſion: which might be confirmed from many other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of their Canons, contrived and drawn up in ſuch a fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and fallacious form. That of <hi>Can.</hi> 28. I have touched already, and the Fraud being detected, I leave the reſt to every ones own Obſervation. And 3. This is done with the greateſt <hi>Solemnity and Formality</hi> that could be, in a Convocation of the Clergy, in the Form of Canons and Decrees, and thoſe ſeverally paſſed as upon particular Debates, with a <hi>Placet eis</hi> to each, and atteſted to have paſſed with one conſent, (under the terms of <hi>Conſtitutions</hi>) by <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft,</hi> for the upper Houſe of the Province of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> by <hi>Overal</hi> for the lower Houſe, and by <hi>Thornborough</hi> for the Province of <hi>York;</hi> whereas thoſe Canons of that Convocation, which were publiſhed, paſſed only the Convocation of the Province of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to conſider the <hi>Conſequences</hi> of it, How <hi>ſcandalous and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious it is to the Chriſtian Religion,</hi> and how <hi>ſcandalous and derogatory to the Authority of the Church of</hi> England, and Convocations of our Clergy, I leave to the Conſideration of others: Likewiſe how <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious</hi> it might have been to the <hi>Civil Government</hi> of Soveraign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and their States, by ſowing the ſeeds of Diſſention between them, had this Convocation Book been publiſhed, and obtained Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or Reputation in the World: But what Work it might have made in the World, may be perceived by what it hath actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally made in theſe Nations, which I will briefly note in ſome <hi>few Obſervations</hi> concerning the <hi>Progreſs and Succeſs</hi> of it, and of this Regal Eccleſiaſtical Faction.</p>
            <p>Whether Archbiſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> had before had any hand in laying
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41226:23"/>down the Plot or not, he lived not to have any ſhare in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Convocation: That Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> (Life of <hi>Laud, Anno</hi> 1610. p. 63.) attributes ſolely to his Succeſſor <hi>Bancroft,</hi> who had before <hi>manag'd <hi>A Secret Corrreſpondence</hi>
               </hi> with K. <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Scotland, inſinuating unto him the Neceſſity of Conſorming both Kingdoms in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Forms of Worſhip, and <hi>laying down a Plot</hi> for reſtoring Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy to that Kirk, without Noiſe or Trouble.</hi> But that Faculty of lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down Plots he notes in them both, and the great Intimacy there was between them. And another ſpecial Qualification in <hi>Bancroft</hi> for ſuch a Work, may be obſerved from that Author, <hi>viz.</hi> a cloſe management of his matters <hi>without noiſe,</hi> and forbearing upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to appear in them himſelf. I have already noted (<hi>p.</hi> 27.) the <hi>Complaints of that Parliament</hi> againſt the <hi>Higher Clergy</hi> for writing Books, and the <hi>Inferiour Clergy</hi> for inveighing from the Pulpits againſt them; and (<hi>pa.</hi> 29.) that Book of Dr. <hi>Cowels,</hi> publiſhed not long after the paſſing the Convocation Book, which may all reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably be judged the Effects of this Work of the Convocation. <hi>Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough</hi> himſelf had before written one, for which he was queſtioned in Parliament. And though <hi>Bancroft</hi> publiſhed none now, yet he failed not to promote the Work otherways, not only by cloſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations, but by open plain Aſſertions, whereof <hi>Coke</hi>'s 12. Report, <hi>pa.</hi> 63. hath a conſiderable Inſtance, and by encouragement of ſuch Principles in the Court, the Univerſities, and all parts. And doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs his Project of a New <hi>Colledge</hi> at <hi>Chelſey,</hi> for which he had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten an Act of Parliament, was principally deſigned for a Seminary of Champions for this Cauſe; and being Chancellor of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> he would not fail to leven and prepare many there for the purpoſe. But Death put an end to his Progreſs and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, 2 <hi>Nov.</hi> 1610.</p>
            <p>But the Faction died not with him: Nor was the Propagation of the Doctrine, even by printed Books, neglected. There was one publiſhed that Year, and dedicated to him by Dr. <hi>Carleton,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Biſhop of <hi>Landaff,</hi> which hath divers paſſages in it to that purpoſe, and others it ſeems there were, which occaſioned new com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints in Parliament the ſame Year. And yet ſo hotly was it ſtill maintained and promoted, that within few Years after was Biſhop <hi>Neile,</hi> (who by the Power and Mediation of <hi>Bancroft,</hi> was made Clerk of the Cloſet, <hi>That ſtanding continnally at the Kings Elbow, he might be ready to perform Good Offices to the Church and Churchmen,</hi> Heyl, p. 60.) for ſeditious Speeches queſtioned in Parliament, till by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tears, and a ſubmiſſive behaviour he got off: But he ſo gained the Favour of his Maſter, that he was preferred to the Deanry of <hi>Weſt min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:41226:24"/>afterwards ſucceſſively to the Biſhopricks of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> (1608.) <hi>Lichfield,</hi> (1609.) <hi>Lincoln,</hi> (1613.) <hi>Durham,</hi> (1617.) by K. <hi>James,</hi> and of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> (1628.) and <hi>York</hi> (1631.) by King <hi>Charles,</hi> after he had been again complained of in Parliament: All which Promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons gave him Opportunity to promote the Work, for which he was an apt and active Agent, in all parts of the Nation.</p>
            <p>Such another Zealot for the Cauſe was <hi>Harſnet</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> who in Parliament time preached ſuch a <hi>Sermon</hi> at <hi>Whitehall</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Text, <hi>Give unto Caeſar,</hi> &amp;c. as gave ſuch Offence, that King <hi>James</hi> was conſtrained to call the Lords and Commons to the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queting Houſe, and calm them with Good words; and the Sermon was burnt, but the Biſhop was afterwards preferred to <hi>Norwich</hi> by K. <hi>James,</hi> and after that to <hi>York</hi> by K. <hi>Charles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like was done by Dr. <hi>Roger Mainwaring,</hi> Chaplain in Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the King, in two Sermons before the King and Court at <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> and after publiſhed, for which he was impeached in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and charged with a <hi>wicked intention to ſeduce and miſguide the Conſcience of the King touching the Obſervation of the Laws,</hi> &amp;c. ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be impriſoned, fined a 1000. <hi>li.</hi> diſabled from Preferments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and his Sermon ſuppreſſed by Proclamation, declaring the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Sentence juſt: Yet was he ſoon after pardoned, preferred to the Rectory of <hi>Stanford Rivers,</hi> void by the promotion of <hi>Mountague</hi> to <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> and had a Diſpenſation to hold it with that of St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s in the Fields, afterwads to the Deanry of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and finally to the Biſhoprick of St. <hi>Davids,</hi> which was highly reſented by the Lords, ſo that the King commanded him not to come to the Parliament, nor ſend any Proxy.</p>
            <p>And this brings me to the Top of all the Faction, who promoted it to its Perfection, or rather Confuſion, <hi>viz.</hi> Dr. <hi>Laud,</hi> againſt whom then Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> Complaint was made to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, that he had warranted theſe Sermons to the Preſs; and <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring</hi> was no ſooner cenſured, but <hi>Lauds</hi> Cauſe was called to the Report. But all further Proceedings againſt him at that time were ſoon ſtopped by Diſſolution of the Parliament, 26 <hi>June,</hi> and 1. <hi>Jul.</hi> had he his <hi>Conge d'eſlier</hi> for Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and ſoon after other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, of which more hereafter.</p>
            <p>Theſe Sermons were preach'd in purſuance of certain <hi>Inſtructions</hi> drawn up by him at the Command of the King, for promoting an illegal Impoſition, under the name of a <hi>Loan;</hi> and being preached at Court, upon ſuch an Occaſion, by a Chaplain in Ordinary, he had no doubt ſome ſpecial Inſtructions, Directions, or Advice in it. In other places the Preachers did their parts according as they were
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41226:24"/>required by the ſaid Inſtructions, amongſt whom <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Beale</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of, and <hi>Sibthorp,</hi> Dr. of Divinity, and in Commiſſion of the Peace, advanc'd the Service, (what he could) in a Sermon at <hi>Northampton</hi> Aſſizes, to the ſame effect with <hi>Mainwaring,</hi> viz. to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the <hi>Lawfulneſs of the Kings impoſing Taxes by his Regal Power, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Conſent in Parliament, and that ſuch Impoſitions bind the Conſcience.</hi> This Sermon was ſent as a ſnare to Archbiſhop <hi>Abbot</hi> to Licenſe at the Kings Command; which he for weighty Reaſons refuſing, it was referred to <hi>Laud,</hi> by whom, after ſome Qualifications and Corrections, it was approved; and then with a Dedication to the King, and a ſtately commendatory Licenſe by <hi>Mountain</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> printed and publiſhed, and the Author afterwards with <hi>Mainwaring</hi> and others, was pardoned at leaſt, if not preferred and rewarded.</p>
            <p>How the reſt did their parts, by inculcating this <hi>Doctrine of the Regal Power</hi> in Impoſing of Taxes without Conſent in Parliament, though directly contrary to one of the moſt certain and known fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental points of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſtitution, through the inſtigation of men of ſuch a Temper and Power as Biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> his old Patron <hi>Neile,</hi> his Tutor <hi>Buckridge, Harſnet, Mountain, Howſon, Curle, Pierce,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Church-Faction,</hi> may be underſtood by what was done by the Lords and Favourites of the <hi>Court-Faction,</hi> there being an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Combination between them, well expreſſed in the beginning of the Inſtructions: For the Gentlemen who refuſed the Loan, were bound by Recogniſance to appear at the Council Table, and many appointed to their ſeveral Commitments in Forreign Counties, and many committed to the <hi>Fleet, Gate-houſe, Marſhalſey, New Priſon;</hi> the common ſort ordered ſome to be enrolled among the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Souldiers, others to be impreſs'd to ſerve in the King's Ships.</p>
            <p>Such <hi>Impoſitions</hi> had been attempted by King <hi>James</hi> in his Time, firſt directly claimed by him as a Right by Letters Pattents, 6 <hi>Jac.</hi> and the Illegality of that being ſhewed, then more indirectly under the Notion of a <hi>Benevolence,</hi> 12 <hi>Jac.</hi> and that alſo being oppoſed as againſt Law, Reaſon, and Religion, <hi>viz.</hi> the King's Oath at his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation, it is an argument of great <hi>Pertinaciouſneſs in the Faction,</hi> that they dare thus impudently aſſert this Right again, which the King himſelf doth in effect diſclaim by requiring it not as a <hi>Tax,</hi> nor ſo much as as a <hi>Benevolence,</hi> but only as a <hi>Loan;</hi> and of a ſtrange <hi>Faſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation upon the King,</hi> to be ſo impoſed upon by theſe Enchantments, as to enforce with ſo much Violence to his Subjects, and probably not without ſome to his own Conſcience, what he could not plainly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert as his Right, or directly claim as his due.</p>
            <p>And ſuch a <hi>Faſcination</hi> is no leſs obſervable in that Exceſs of his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41226:25"/>Affection to this Faction in oppoſition to his Parliament, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the Conſtancy of his ſpecial Favour to ſuch of them as the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cenſured, ſoon after conferred upon them, and (as in the caſe of <hi>Mainwaring</hi>) though he himſelf had publickly declared the ſentence juſt. Certainly this on both ſides was Paſſion, no leſs than what the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or the Rage of an unlawful Luſt, as if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicated by that abominable Magical Love Potion of the Golden Cup. And if we look a little further into the Story, we ſhall meet more Evidence of ſuch an <hi>Intoxication</hi> in the <hi>Inconſiſtence of the King's Actions,</hi> having the next Year in full Parliament ſolemnly granted that moſt juſt and reaſonable <hi>Petition of Rights,</hi> and ſo confirmed them by a New Act, and yet nevertheleſs before the next Seſſion, through theſe Enchantments, violating the ſame in as groſs manner as ever before.</p>
            <p>But I need not to note more of <hi>ſuch illegal Projects</hi> or <hi>Practices,</hi> which were various, and perſiſted in till they came to the uſual De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of ſuch Publick Differences, the Sword and Civil War, by the ſevere Judgment of God upon the King and the whole Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For they are freſh in Memory of many living, and obvious in printed Books; and that they all proceeded upon the ſame <hi>Principles,</hi> may be underliood both by the <hi>Perſons</hi> who had then the chief Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of Affairs, and by that <hi>Solemn Declaration of their Principle,</hi> which may be looked upon as the concluding Act of the Faction, which ſealed up all, their Canons and Decrees made in their Synod 1640. continued <hi>durante beneplacito,</hi> by a New Commiſſion after the Parliament diſſolved.</p>
            <p>There was a perfect <hi>Combination</hi> between the two Factions, and both proceeded upon the ſame <hi>common Principle</hi> in matters of State, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made matter of Religion, by that means the Church Faction could not but be concerned in all. And though that was not ſo rampant while <hi>Abbot</hi> was Archbiſhop, yet was it then ſtrongly promoted by <hi>Neal</hi> and others, at laſt overpowered him, and when his Succeſſor <hi>Laud</hi> got up, carried all both in Church and State, (rid the Beaſt.) He was a fierce Oppoſer of all, who differed from him in Eccleſiaſtical Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as Puritans, or in Civil Matters, as Republicans, was <hi>Anno</hi> 1608. recommended by his Tutor <hi>Buckridge</hi> to the ſervice of <hi>Neal,</hi> and by him afterward to K. <hi>James,</hi> by whom he was gradually raiſed, at laſt to the Biſhoprick of St. <hi>Davids, Anno</hi> 1621. and came to that Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authority with <hi>Buckingham,</hi> that he made him his Confeſſor and Counſellor: and in the beginning of the next Reign, grew as <hi>much into the King's Favour, as before he had been in the Dukes, becoming as it were his Majeſties Secretary for all Church Concernments:</hi> was made
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41226:25"/>Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> and Dean of the Chappel, 1626. and 1628. after Complaint againſt him in Parliament, Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Councellor, (together with his old Patron <hi>Neal</hi>) and after the Dukes Death he is <hi>called to the Helm</hi> of the State, and <hi>ſteers the Courſe thereof by his Directions.</hi> About the ſame time was Sir <hi>Th Wentworth,</hi> afterward E. of <hi>Straffod,</hi> by the Treaſurer <hi>Weſton</hi> brought over to that Party, made a Privy Councellor, and became the moſt devour Friend of the Church, the greateſt Zealot for advancing the Monarchical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; and <hi>Laud</hi> and he coming to a right underſtanding, entred into a League of inviolable Friendſhip, and joyning Hearts and Hands together, co-operated from thenceforth for advancing the Honour of the Church and his Majeſty's Service. Such another intimate with him, and Friend of the Church, was the Attorney General <hi>Noy,</hi> who projected the Ship Money, whoſe death he much lamented. And ſuch another Sir <hi>Fr. Windebank,</hi> for whom he obtained the place of Secretary of State. Upon the Death of the E. of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> 1630. he was choſen Chancellor of the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and upon the death of <hi>Abbot,</hi> 1633. immediately made Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> And how the ſeed ſown in the dark in the former Convocation, was cultivated and propagated by ſuch ſtrenuous Labourers, and the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of Majeſty, till it appeared in it's full maturity in the next, may eaſily be conceived without reciting any more particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Convocation</hi> there were three things, which <hi>Canterbury</hi> was to take ſpecial care of, the Regal Power, the Epiſcopal Power, and Uniformity. <q>For the <hi>Regal Power,</hi> they decree that the <hi>Order</hi> of Kings is of Divine Right, the Ordinance of God, founded in the prime Laws of Nature, and clearly eſtabliſhed by expreſs Texts of Scripture: That a <hi>Supream Power</hi> is given to this Order by God himſelf, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all, and puniſh with the Temporal Sword all ſtubborn and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doers: That the care of God's Church is committed to Kings in Scripture, and her Government belongs in chief to Kings: That the Power to call and diſſolve Councils is the true Right of all Chriſtian Kings: That to avow in any of their Realms, any Independant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active Power, either Papal or Popular, is to undermine their Regal Office: That for Subjects to bear Arms againſt their King upon any pretence whatſoever, is at leaſt to reſiſt the Powers which are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God: That Tribute, Cuſtom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all manner of ſupport and ſupply is due to Kings from their Subjects by the Law of God, Nature, and Nations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> And they ordain this to be read by every Parſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> every quarter of the Year, under pain of ſuſpenſion, and that no Eccleſiaſtical or Academical Perſon ſhall maintain or abett any
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41226:26"/>Poſition in oppoſition or Impeachment of any part thereof under pain of Excommunication.</p>
            <p>Now if this be true, which they have decreed, then have <hi>all Kings the ſame</hi> Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>jure divino,</hi> which cannot be reſtrain'd by any humane Conſtitution; then are all thoſe Conſtitutions of Government, whereby a <hi>limited Power</hi> only is given to the King, though ſettled by ſolemn Agreement, and mutual Oaths for Obſervation and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof, all void, as to any Limitations, as derogatory to the Law of God, and the King may, and muſt uſe his Power, which he hath <hi>jure divino;</hi> and then are all thoſe, who inſiſt upon any Right by any ſuch Laws, which is inconſiſtent with that Plenitude of Royal Power <hi>jure divino,</hi> factious and ſeditious, and to be puniſhed with the Temporal Sword as ſtubborn and wicked doers. But if all Forms of <hi>Government</hi> when throughly ſettled, have Gods Authority, and the Powers that be (in each) be ordained of God; if <hi>Publick Pacts</hi> and Agreements (by which Governments are uſually conſtituted and ratified) are to be obſerved inviolably <hi>jure naturali;</hi> and if <hi>Solemn Oaths</hi> (by which Pacts and Agreements are uſually confirmed, and made as Sacred and Inviolable as may be) are to be obſerved moſt religiouſly and <hi>jure divino,</hi> then is their Doctrine falſe, factious and ſeditious, and tending to the Subverſion or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance of moſt Kingdoms in this Part of the World, and of our own in particular, and was therefore juſtly condemned by the next Parliament; then is the <hi>Church of England</hi> in Convocation, and her Doctrine no leſs <hi>fallible</hi> than the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and then was that Faction the great <hi>Occaſion of our late Civil Wars,</hi> by miſleading the Conſciences of the King and of a great part of the People, of great Abuſes by <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Clauſes, inconſiſtent</hi> with the Conſtitution of our Government, <hi>obtruded into divers Acts of Parliament,</hi> and of many illegal Arbitrary Acts in the Reigns ſince; is ſtill the occaſion of our Civil Diſſentions and Unſettlement, and of much of our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointments under the preſent Government at this day, and will continue ſo to be till either ſome good Counſel and Reſolution put an end to it, or it produce another Civil War.</p>
            <p>For while Princes, and ſome part of the People ſhall be perſwaded upon pretended Principles of Religion, that the Regal Power is <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> above all Humane Laws; and the reſt know that it anciently hath been, and to this day is very different all over the World, in all Kingdoms, according to their ſeveral Conſtitutions, in ſome more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, as the Eaſtern, and the Roman Emperors, in others very little, as divers of the Northern, and particularly the <hi>German</hi> from whom the <hi>Engliſh</hi> deſcended, who acted in Council <hi>Authoritate ſuadendi magis quam Jubendi Poteſtate,</hi> and that by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution it is limited, and confined to the obſervance of Law in all parts of it; this muſt be a perpetual Cauſe or <hi>Occaſion of Diſſenſions,</hi> which are apt to break out at laſt into Wars. But if the <hi>Occaſions of that Error</hi> being obſerved, it be well conſidered, that the Power of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Kings, the Roman Emperors, or any other, is no Rule for the meaſure of our Government, where the greateſt Power of all is manifeſtly not in the King, but remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the whole Body of King, Lords and Commons: That Expreſſions in ſome Acts of Parliament, Articles of Religion, or Canons, uſed and intended meerly in Oppoſition to Papal Pretences, ought not captiouſly to be extended to what was not intended, or in queſtion contrary to manifeſt Truth: That Expreſſions in the <hi>Homilies</hi> out of Zeal againſt Conſpiracies and Rebellions of Papiſts are of no Authority in Queſtions or Controverſies of State, nor Deerees of Univerſities, when to ſerve a Faction, or pleaſe thoſe from whom they expect Preferment: and That Ambition, Self-intereſt, and Flattery, the uſual Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants of Princes Courts, are always the promoters of ſuch Pretences: the Faction will ſoon be deſerted by all honeſt men; and then may we hope for a Happy Settlement, which is the Deſign of this Paper, and the ſincere Deſire of it's Author.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41226:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
